<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="jto_custom_schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="jto_custom_schema.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Afric-American Picture Gallery</title>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Text encoded by</resp>
               <name>
                  <forename>Elizabeth</forename>
                  <surname>Hopwood</surname>
               </name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Distributed as part of the American Antiquarian Society's Just Teach One: Early
               African American Print. </p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>electronic edition</p>
         </sourceDesc>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="frederick_douglass"/>
               <person xml:id="attucks"/>
               <person xml:id="george_washington"/>
               <person xml:id="thomas_jefferson"/>
               <person xml:id="touissant_loverture"/>
               <person xml:id="edward_everett"/>
               <person xml:id="ira_aldridge"/>
               <person xml:id="thomas_onward"/>
               <person xml:id="henry_clay"/>
               <person xml:id="daniel_webster"/>
               <person xml:id="john_calhoun"/>
               <person xml:id="bernice"/>
               <person xml:id="phillis_wheatley"/>
               <person xml:id="selena_hastings"/>
               <person xml:id="benjamin_banneker"/>
               <person xml:id="alexander_hamilton"/>
               <person xml:id="henry_sipkins"/>
               <person xml:id="james_forten"/>
               <person xml:id="hezekiah_grice"/>
               <person xml:id="william_hinton"/>
               <person xml:id="bird"/>
               <person xml:id="burr"/>
               <person xml:id="john_bowers"/>
               <person xml:id="vanbrackle"/>
               <person xml:id="george_vashon"/>
               <person xml:id="watkins"/>
               <person xml:id="corr"/>
               <person xml:id="cornish"/>
               <person xml:id="easton"/>
               <person xml:id="rush"/>
               <person xml:id="peter_williams"/>
               <person xml:id="theodore_wright"/>
               <person xml:id="bill"/>
               <person xml:id="jd_esq"/>
            </listPerson>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p>The encoding methodology for this document marks formatting and structural details,
            including the following: <list>
               <item>front</item>
               <item>body</item>
               <item>paragraphs</item>
               <item>columns</item>
               <item>page breaks</item>
               <item>quotations</item>
               <item>textual divisions</item>
               <item>bylines</item>
               <item>dates</item>
               <item>section headers</item>
               <item>emphasis</item>
            </list> Person and place names were marked using <persName/> and <placeName/>.
            Geographical landmarks were marked with <geogName/>. Persons named in the text were
            given corresponding pointers in the listPerson. Full names (forenames and surnames) were
            provided in the listPerson whenever possible. </p>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <pb n="52"/>
            <dateline>Feb 1859</dateline>
            <head>Afric-American Picture Gallery.</head>
            <byline>BY ETHI0P.</byline>
            <cb/>
            <head><lb/>NUMBER I.</head>
            <p>I always had a <hi rend="italic">penchant</hi> for pictures. From a chit of a boy
               till now, my love for beautiful, or quaint old pictures has been unquenched. </p>
            <p>If an ever abiding love for any branch of <hi rend="italic">Art</hi> is indicative of
               a fitness to pursue it, then I should have been a painter. Even when so small as to
               be almost imperceptible, I used to climb up, by the aid of a stool, to my mother's
               mantle piece, take down the old family almanac and study its pictures with a greater
               relish than ever a fat alderman partook of a good dinner including a bountiful supply
               of the choicest wines. All this however, never made me a painter. Fate marked <cb/>
               out a rougher, sterner destiny for me. But the habit of rambling in search of, and
               hunting up curious, old, or rare and beautiful pictures, is as strong as ever. </p>
            <p>It was in one of these rambles, that I stumbled over the Afric-American Picture
               Gallery, which has since become one of my dearest retreats wherein to spend many an
               otherwise weary hour, with profit and pleasure[.] </p>
            <p>The collection is quite numerous, having been sought from every quarter of the
               American continent, and some from abroad; and though as a <hi rend="italic">Gallery
                  of Art</hi>, if not highly meritorious, still from its wide range of subjects and
               the ingenuity with which <pb n="53"/><cb/> many of items are presented, it must, to
               the lover and curious in such matters, afford much for amusement, and to the careful
               observer and the thinker much that is valuable and interesting. </p>
            <p>In style and excellence these pictures vary according to the fancy or skill of the
               artist. Some are finely executed, while others are mere rough sketches. Some are in
               oil, some in water colors, and India Ink shadings, a few statues, statuettes, and a
               few Crayons and Pencilings possessing a high degree of merit; others are mere
               charcoal sketches and of little worth beyond the subjects they portray. </p>
            <p>But without pursuing this general outline further, let the reader, with me enter into
               this almost unknown Gallery. Well, here we are, and looking about us. </p>
            <p>The first thing noticeable, is the unstudied arrangement of these pictures. They seem
               rather to have been put up out of the way, many of them, than hung for any effect. </p>
            <p>The walls are spacious, and contain ample room for more, and, in many instances,
               better paintings; and many niches yet vacant for busts and statues; and just here,
               let me make an humble petition in behalf of this our newly discovered
               Gallery.&#x2014;It is that generous artists, will, at their convenience, have the
               goodness to paint an occasional picture, or chisel a statue or bust, and we will be
               sure to assign it to its appropriate place. But let us take a survey, and speak only
               of what strikes us most forcibly in our present mood.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>PICTURE NUMBER 1.—THE SLAVE SHIP. </head>
            <p>This picture hangs near the entrance, on the south side of the Gallery, and in rather
               an unfavorable light.</p>
            <p>The view is of course <placeName>Jamestown harbor, Virginia</placeName>, in 1609, and
               has all the wild surroundings of that portion of our country at that period; the
               artist having been faithful even to every shrub, crag and nook. Off in the mooring
               lays the <hi rend="italic">slave ship</hi>, Dutch-modeled and ugly, even hideous to
               look upon, as a slave-ship ought to be. On the <cb/> shore is a group of emaciated
                  <hi rend="italic">Africans</hi>, heavily manacled, the first slaves that ever trod
               the American continent; while in the fierce and angry waters of the bay, which seem
               to meet the black and dismal and storm-clad sky, is seen a small boat containing
               another lot of these human beings, just nearing the shore. </p>
            <p>If the artist's general conception of, this picture may be regarded a success, in its
               details, beyond all question, this is its crowning point. The small boat struck by,
               and contending with a huge breaker, is so near the shore that you can behold, and
               startle as you behold, the emaciated and death-like faces of the unfortunate victims,
               and the hideous countenances of their captors; and high and above all, perched upon
               the stern, with foot, tail and horns, and the chief insignias of his office, is his
               Satanic Majesty, gloating over the whole scene. </p>
            <p>What is more truthful than that the devil is ever the firm friend and companion of
               the slave ship? </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>PICTURE NUMBER 2.—THE FIRST AND THE LAST COLORED EDITOR.</head>
            <p>This small, but neat picture hangs on the north side of the gallery; and though
               simple in its details, is so well executed that it has much attracted me. </p>
            <p>The Last Colored Editor, quite a young man, with a finely formed head and ample
               brow&#x2014;thoughtful, earnest, resolute&#x2014;sits in chair editorial, with the
               first number of the Freedom's Journal, the first journal ever edited by, and devoted
               to the cause of the colored man in America, held in one hand and outspread before
               him, while the other, as though expressive of his resolve, is firmly clenched.</p>
            <p>Surrounding him are piles of all the journals edited by colored men from the
               commencement up till the present, among which the Freedom's Journal, Colored
               American, People's Press, North Star, and <persName ref="#frederick_douglass"
                  >Frederick Douglas</persName>'s paper are the more prominent. The First Editor is
               represented as a vener<pb n="54" type="wordbreaking"/>
               <cb/>able old man, with whitened locks and placid face, leaning on a staff, and
               unperceived by the Last Editor, is looking intently over his shoulder on the
               outspread journal. </p>
            <p>It is his own first editorial, and the first ever penned and published by a colored
               man in <placeName>America</placeName>. The scene is the linking together of our once
               scarcely hopeful past with the now bright present.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>PICTURE NO. 3—THE FIRST MARTYR OF THE REVOLUTION. </head>
            <p>This is a head of <persName ref="#attucks">Attucks</persName>. It may not be
               generally known, and it may not be particularly desirable that the public should
               know, that the First Martyr of the American Revolution was a colored man; that the
               first bosom that was bared to the blast of war was black; the first blood that
               drenched the path-way which led up to American liberty, was from the veins of a
               colored man. </p>
            <p>And yet such is the fact; and the artist has done a service in the execution of this
               head. It hangs at the north east end of the Gallery, and is a fine likeness of a
               bold, vigorous man,&#x2014;just such, as would be likely to head a revolution to
               throw off oppression. May the name of <persName ref="#attucks">Attucks</persName> and
               the facts connected therewith never perish.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>PICTURE NO. 4. SUNSET IN ABBEOKUTA.</head>
            <p>This is a fine painting. The landscape is rich, varied, beautiful. The sky has all
               the warmth of hue and softness of tint, and all that gorgeousness (changing seemingly
               with every instant,) for which an African sky is so much noted. No rainbow with us,
               in its full splendor, is so variegated or so wide in its range of colors. </p>
            <p>The last touches of the artist's pencil has made the glow of the coming evening to
               softly spread itself over here and there a dusky inhabitant reclining upon the banks
               of an unrippled lake. The effect is fine, and the <cb/> whole scene is so charming
               that one could almost wish to be there. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>PICTURES 5 AND 6—THE UNDER GROUND RAILROAD.</head>
            <p>In these two pictures the artist is certainly quite up to our idea. They are of large
               size and represent both the Southern and Northern portions of that mysterious road.
               They hang beside each other on the south side of the Gallery and are marked A and B.
               I would suggest, that B be changed over to the north wall, as a more appropriate
               place. Picture A, or the south view represents a dark road leading through a darker
               forest, along which is seen merely some twenty pairs of fine stalwart human feet and
               legs&#x2014;male and female&#x2014;of all sizes, hurrying northward. Every muscle and
               limb indicates firmness and resolution.</p>
            <p>The scene is night-time, and far distant through the forest is faintly seen the north
               star&#x2014;small but bright and unfailing, and to the fugitive, unerring. </p>
            <p>Picture B on the north view consists of some twenty bold heads and fine robust faces,
               each of which is lit up with a joy no pen can portray, and nothing but the pencil of
               the master could have reached. The exclamation of each must be <said>we have found
                  it!!!</said>
            </p>
            <p>In the foreground is a lake and the back ground is a Canadian forest, through which
               here and there you can perceive a small rustic cottage. Both of these pictures
               sustain well that air of mystery which envelopes the Under Ground Rail Road.</p>
            <p>In the first view we have but the feet and legs; indicating the mysterious manner in
               which those feet and legs move bodies towards freedom, or pass along that undefined
               and undefinable Road that leads to liberty.</p>
            <p>There is another thought. The head, the recognized seat of the mind, is useless to
               the slave, or, if of service to him, this thinking apparatus is not <pb n="55"/>
               <cb/> his own ; it belongs to his owner; hence he makes use of his feet and legs, or
               the physical machinery; while in the second view, at the northern end of this
               undefinable Road, where <cb/> liberty is, the head or mental part is presented to
               view. The slave,&#x2014;the chattel,&#x2014;the thing is a <hi rend="italic"
               >man</hi>.</p>
            <p> (<hi rend="italic">To be Continued.</hi>)</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <pb n="87"/>
            <dateline>MAR 1859</dateline>
            <head>Afric-American Picture Gallery.—SECOND PAPER.</head>
            <byline>BY ETHI0P.</byline>
            <head>PICTURE VII. TOUISSANT L'OVERTURE.</head>
            <cb/>
            <p>Pictures are teachings by example. From them we often derive our best lessons. A
               picture of a once beloved mother, an almost forgotten grandfather whose image perhaps
               we bear, or a long lost child, once the centre of our affections; such a picture
               occasionally taken down from its hiding-place, and looked at, calls up associations
               and emotions, and produces troops of thought that paint the memory afresh with hues
               the most beautiful, touching, beneficial and lasting. A picture of a great man with
               whose acts we are familiar, calls up the whole history of his times. Our minds thus
               become re-impressed with the events and we arrive at the philosophy of them. </p>
            <p>A picture of <persName ref="#george_washington">Washington</persName> recalls to mind
               the American Revolution, and the early history of the Republic. A picture of
                  <persName ref="#thomas_jefferson">Thomas Jefferson</persName> brings before the
               mind in all its scope and strength that inimitable document, the Declaration of
               Independence; and in addition, carries us forward to the times, when its broad and
               eternal principles, will be fully recognised by, and applied to the entire American
               people. I had these conclusions forced upon me by looking not upon either the picture
               of Washington or Jefferson in the gallery. Far from it; but by a most beautiful
               portrait of one of the greatest men the world ever saw&#x2014;<persName
                  ref="#touissant_loverture">Touissant L'Overture</persName>. This painting hangs in
               the south east corner of the Gallery in a favourable position and in good light as it
               ought; as it portrays the features of one of God's and Earth's noblemen long since
               retired.</p>
            <cb/>
            <p>Far be it from me to venture to a description of either the picture or the man. I
               have no pencil and no pen with which I can do it. Some future historian in other
               times, will yet write the name of <persName ref="#touissant_loverture">Touissant L'
                  Overture</persName> higher and in purer light than that of any man that has lived
               up to to-day. But the special point to which I wish to call attention, and upon which
               I may venture a remark, is the long and interesting train of historical facts in
               relation to <placeName>Hayti</placeName>, that gem of the sea, this portrait
               associates in the mind of the intelligent beholder. To say nothing of him who led the
               breathings of this people after liberty; the breaking in pieces the yoke that galled
               them their heroic struggles, the routing finally and utterly from the soil their
               oppressors; their almost superhuman efforts thereafter, to rise from the low state in
               which the degradation of slavery and chains had placed them and their final triumph
               over every obstacle; in fine the whole history from first to last of this Island and
               this people is so vividly brought before the mind, by merely this likeness of the
               inimitable <persName ref="#touissant_loverture">Touissant L'Overture</persName>, that
               it is re-impressed with the extraordinary, <hi rend="italic">useful and touching
                  lesson it teaches.</hi></p>
         </div>

         <div>
            <head>PICTURE VIII.&#x2014;SOLOUQUE AND HIS COURT.</head>
            <p>If any thing else was needed to carry the mind over the field of Haytian events, and
               complete our history; or in leading us for the first time to study that history, this
               additional picture ought to be sufficient. It is of largest size, consisting of
               portraits of the sable Emperor and the magnates that move round his Imperial person;
               and hangs <pb n="88"/> beside that of <persName ref="#touissant_loverture"
                  >L'Overture</persName>. The various descriptions given me of these persons lead me
               to believe, that these likenesses, unlike many that have been gotten up for the <hi
                  rend="italic">American prejudice Market</hi>, are genuine and up to the originals.
               That of the Emperor's is superior as he is known to be a superior looking man. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>PICTURE IX.&#x2014;MOUNT VERNON.</head>
            <p>Our artist must have taken time by the forelock in the execution of this picture; as
                  <placeName>MOUNT VERNON</placeName> has become of late the great popular theme of
               the American people. <placeName>Mount Vernon</placeName> just now enters into
               everything. It has something to do with every spring of the machinery of American
               society; social, political, and religious. It is <placeName>Mount Vernon</placeName>
               in the pulpit, <placeName>Mount Vernon</placeName> on the rostrum, <placeName>Mount
                  Vernon</placeName> from the Press, <placeName>Mount Vernon</placeName> from every
               lip. </p>
            <p>The boys in the streets busily cry out <placeName>Mount Vernon</placeName>; the
               fashionable young belle simpers <placeName>Mount Vernon</placeName>.</p>
            <p><placeName>Mount Vernon</placeName> exclaims the breast-laden patriot;
                  <placeName>Mount Vernon</placeName> echoes the good old ladies, <placeName>Mount
                  Vernon</placeName> is piped, <placeName>Mount Vernon</placeName> is harped;
                  <placeName>Mount Vernon</placeName> is danced; <placeName>Mount Vernon</placeName>
               is sung. Even men walk by the aid of <placeName>Mount Vernon</placeName> canes,
               manufactured from some of its decaying relics. And what is <placeName>Mount
                  Vernon</placeName>? </p>
            <p><placeName>Mount Vernon</placeName> as the readers must know is a spot of earth
               somewhere in <placeName>Virginia</placeName>, and once the Home of the Father of his
               Country. How careful ought we to be, then, in word or deed about <placeName>Mount
                  Vernon</placeName>. </p>
            <p>I must plead in excuse, therefore, that in the conception of this picture, the Artist
               has simply failed; if not in faithfulness to the original, certainly in gratifying
               the popular American feeling. The Picture hangs on the south side of the Gallery, and
               in excellent light. </p>
            <p>It is of largest size, exhibiting the grounds, the mansion, out-house, slave huts and
               all; once planned, laid out, and erected with so much care by <cb/><persName
                  ref="#george_washington"><hi rend="italic">Washington</hi></persName>; but now
               alas, all in a state of dilapidation and decay. Decay is written by the Artist's
               pencil more legibly than in letters, on everything. &#x2014;On the house top, on the
               door sill is written decay. On the chimney, on the gables, on the eaves, is written
               decay. The consuming fingers of decay and dilapidation mark each and every out
               house.&#x2014;Every old slave hut, like so many specters shadows forth decay.
               &#x2014;Decay stands staring in the gate-ways, staring in the porches, staring in the
               cellars.&#x2014; The very wind which bends the here and there scattering tree-tops,
               (land marks of the past) seem to creak through the many visible crevices of the Old
               Mansion and sigh decay, decay! decay!! </p>
            <p>I never saw <placeName>Mount Vernon</placeName>; and as I gaze upon this Picture I
               ask myself is it true? Is this the home of the <hi rend="italic">Father of his
                  Country?</hi> Is it, that, every thing <persName ref="#george_washington"
                  >Washington</persName> possessed should so perish? Or, so perish the all, that we
               should have left to us, but his name; and yet with a tendency to forget names however
               great, I am at a loss to know how we shall preserve even the name of <persName
                  ref="#george_washington">Washington</persName> many years longer. </p>
            <p>But there is another feature in this Picture besides the stern solemn passing away,
               that I desire to direct attention to. The Artist has located, and I suppose correctly
               enough, on the banks, where sluggishly glides the <geogName>Potomac</geogName>'s
               waters, the TOMB OF <persName ref="#george_washington">WASHINGTON</persName>. </p>
            <p>The first thing that here arrests the eye is the recently dug up coffin of <persName
                  ref="#george_washington">Washington</persName>; just behind which stands the ghost
               of his faithful old slave and body servant; while in front, a living slave of to-day
               stands, with the <hi rend="italic">bones</hi> of <persName ref="#george_washington"
                  >Washington</persName> gathered up in his arms, and labelled <q>'For Sale'</q>
               <q>'Price $200,000 ; this negro included.'</q>
               <q>'Money wanted.</q>"&#x2014;A number of other slaves, men, women, and children, are
               placed in a row along the bank just beyond, bearing about the neck of each the
               following inscription: <hi rend="italic">These negroes for sale. Money
               wanted.</hi>'</p>
            <pb n="89"/>
            <p>Proceeding from the Old Mansion to the <hi rend="italic">Tomb</hi>, are two elderly,
               portly, aristocratic looking gentlemen, bearing unmistakable evidences of being the
               present proprietors of the <placeName>Mount Vernon</placeName> estate, and celebrated
               relatives of the great Virginian, and Father of his Country; and a noted son of
               Massachusetts. These gentlemen are followed towards the tomb by a few pious looking
               old ladies. </p>
            <p>Such is but a faint description of this picture of <placeName>Mount
                  Vernon</placeName>; and as obscurely as it is hung in our midst, <persName
                  ref="#edward_everett">Edward Everett</persName> the distinguished limner of
                  <persName ref="#george_washington">Washington</persName> should see it, and if
               any, point out its defects. </p>
            <p>Our Gallery begins to draw. Numerous have been the inquiries about it, and two
               individuals who after sundry searchings and pryings have found out our <hi
                  rend="italic">secret</hi>.&#x2014;Our pleasant hiding-place, where we have so
               often and so long shut up ourselves from the blast and chill of the world, is no
               longer our own. The luxury of solitude is even gone, gone forever!</p>
            <p>Just as I had finished the sketch of the last picture, (luckily for me) and pointed
               my pencil for another, the little brown-faced boy in attendance, bowed in, to my
               great surprise, a very respectable appearing gentleman&#x2014;a little seedy, though
               very genteel with all notwithstanding&#x2014;and not Anglo African, but Anglo-Saxon,
               or Anglo American or something of that sort; botheration, I never could get the hang
               of these Angloes! but no matter, he was genteel in manner and intellectual in
               appearance. ' </p>
            <p>'<said>I read your Picture Sketches in the last number of the Anglo-African Magazine,
                  and have sought out your Gallery,</said>' said he. <said>'Well, what do you think
                  of it?'</said> said I. <said>'Your Gallery? well, I must examine it,&#x2014;but
                  your Magazine! !!'</said>
               <said>'Magazine,'</said> rejoined I, <said>'yes, that is the question.'</said>
               <said>'Your magazine,'</said> said he (not regarding the interruption) <said>'is
                  uncalled for.'</said> I started up. <said>'I am a well-known friend to your
                  race.'</said> I started a little more up right, and said, <said>'my dear sir, if
                  you <cb/></said><said>mean Anglo-Africans, well; but do not say <q>your
                  race.</q>'</said> here I brought my fist down on the table, added&#x2014;
                  <said>there is but one <hi rend="italic">race of men on the face of the earth, sir
                     ! ! !'</hi></said> Our visitor colored a little. <said>'I was about to
                  remark,'</said> he said, <said>'that if your men had capacity they might write for
                  our anti-slavery journals and other ably conducted magazines in the country, such
                  as <title rend="none">Harpers'</title> or the <title rend="none">Atlantic
                     Monthly</title>. It would be more creditable. You don't want a separate
                  magazine and pen up your thoughts there.'</said>
               <said>'The <q>"Anglo-African"</q> is not such as you designate it,'</said> said I,
                  <said>'it is simply headed by colored men, but excludes no man on account of his
                  color from its pages, and it were unfortunate,'</said> I said this with emphasis,
                  <said>'that since colored men are the oppressed, it were unfortunate that every
                  anti-slavery journal in the country is not edited by colored men.'</said> This was
               a little too sharp, and our new friend colored more deeply than before. <said>'What
                  do you think of that statue of <persName ref="#ira_aldridge">Ira
                     Aldridge</persName>, just over on the other side of the Gallery, there?'</said>
               said I, as anxious to turn the conversation as he was. He examined it a few moments
               and said, '<said>It is quite a clever attempt for&#x2014;'</said> he was about to add
               something more, but suddenly turning asked who modelled it. <said>'All I
                  know,'</said> said I, <said>'is, <persName ref="#ida_aldridge">Mr.
                     Aldridge</persName> went from this country to <placeName>Europe</placeName>
                  when quite a young man, took to the stage, his color being no bar to eminence
                  there, and step by step he has ascended until now he stands on the very highest
                  round of the actor's ladder. He stands today, as an actor, the most renowned in
                  the world. The statue before us I believe was model led in Europe.'</said> Our
               visitor hastily glanced at it again, and pronounced it excellent, adding a few
               criticisms about its breadth of forehead and a few doubts about its want of faithful
               ness to the original, he passed around the Gallery. I sat down again to make a sketch
               of this plaster statue of <persName ref="#ida_aldridge">Aldridge</persName>, the
               world-renowned actor (by the way, an excellent model of him as <pb n="90"/>
               <cb/> Othello), when our little brown-faced boy bowed his head in the doorway, and
               announced this time a lady&#x2014;a colored lady. I laid down my pencil, and though
               much confused, tried my hand at politeness. The lady, plainly, but neatly attired and
               rather stiff, was all politeness, but it was of that kind that first chills, and then
               freezes you. Eye-glass up, and with sarcastic smile, she hurriedly scanned several of
               the pictures. Her air was a dissatisfied one in the outset; she had come to find
               fault and quarrel with our poor Gallery from the first. I felt this, and determined
               on revenge. <said>'What nonsense is all this!'</said> she exclaimed, and proceeded to
               criticise quite freely. I caught up my pencil, and wrote: <said>'An old maid; a
                  little dimmed in sight; somewhat faded, but a few good traces of beauty yet left:
                  face a little too sharp, and eye too restless and a little prudish with all: quite
                  ready in speech, but rather too second-hand in opinion.'</said> I stopped. A kind
               of nervous feeling came over me, and I began to fumble for my knife, to scratch the
               words <hi rend="italic">old</hi>, <hi rend="italic">dimmed</hi>, and all the other
               unpleasant adjectives I had thrown into my sentences, for in truth she was not old,
               though I learned afterwards <cb/>she was a maid. My lady friend perceiving my
               embarrassed manner, laid it to her own superciliousness, and her eye dilated at the
               supposed effect and proceeded freely with her criticisms. My old revenge came back
               upon me: <said>'Madam, or mam,'</said> said I at last, <said>'these pictures, as a
                  whole, make no claim to the high artistic merit you look for in them, though I
                  think some of them rather clever as works of <hi rend="italic">art</hi>; but they
                  serve as simple reminders of what the people of color were, now are, and will yet
                  be. What they have gone through, are going through, and have yet to go
                  through.'</said> This last speech of mine had the desired effect. With glass still
               to her eye, she passed on in her strictures, and on, too, in the Gallery. I adjusted
               myself again to make the sketch of <persName ref="#ida_aldridge"><hi rend="italic"
                     >Aldridge</hi></persName>, and taking position, looked up for the purpose. Lo,
               and behold! my visitors were both gone. I was alone. My paper for my intended sketch
               was scribbled out, and my pencil whittled away. Bothered and puzzled, I snatched up
               my hat and started for the door, bidding the boy at the same time to bar it against
               all further intruders, I rushed into the street.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <pb n="100"/>
            <dateline>APR 1859</dateline>
            <head>Afric-American Picture Gallery. THIRD PAPER.</head>
            <byline>BY ETHI0P.</byline>
            <cb/>
            <head>PICTURE NO. X.—A NEW PICTURE.</head>
            <p>Our gallery Boy who barred its doors so firmly against intruders, has just entered
               the Gallery with his own likeness, and desires that it may be hung up ; and, for more
               reasons than one he shall be gratified. The picture comes to us in mien pleasant,
               smiling, and as fresh as nature itself. </p>
            <p>This boy <persName ref="#thomas_onward"><hi rend="italic">Thomas
                  Onward</hi></persName> (I call him <persName ref="#thomas_onward">Tom</persName>
               for shortness,) though he has seen all of life—yea more, is not an <hi rend="italic"
                  >Old Tom</hi> by any means; nor an <hi rend="italic">Uncle Tom</hi>, nor a <hi
                  rend="italic">Saintly Tom</hi>, nor even what is commonly deemed a good Tom; but a
               shrewd little rogue, a real live <hi>Young Tom</hi>, up to all conceivable mischief
               and equal to all emergencies. He is a perfect model of a little fellow in his way,
               and a fair representative of his class. Sound in limb, symmetrical in form and robust
               in health, jovial, frank, easy mannered and handsome-infinitely so compared with even
               the likeness I hold, one would scarcely conclude that this boy has come down to us
               through nearly three hundred years of hard trial.</p>
            <cb/>
            <p>And yet it is true. Such is his history. He was almost whipped into existence,
               whipped into childhood, whipped up to boyhood. He has been whipped up to manhood,
               whipped down to old age, whipped out of existence. He was toiled into life; he has
               been toiled through life; toiled out of life. He has been robbed of his toil, robbed
               of his body, robbed of all but his soul.</p>
            <p>He has been hated for what he was, hated for what he was not, and hated for what he
               ought to have been. He has been dreaded because of his ignorance, and dreaded because
               of his knowledge, dreaded for his weakness, dreaded for his strength. </p>
            <p>Noble, innocent boy! hadst thou been able to remember a tithe of the hard things done
               to thee ; or hadst thou known a tithe of the hard things said of thee ; or of the
               hard feelings entertained towards thee, it would be difficult to conjecture the
               result. But out of all these mountains of dust and ashes without one bit of sackcloth
               upon thee, hast thou come forth fresh, smiling and free. <hi rend="italic">Tom, Tom !
                  ! !</hi>
               <pb n="100"/><cb/>Who shall write a fitting apostrophe to thee and thy rising
               fortunes. </p>
            <p>What sorry figures do the hard, grave, iron, half savage and half barbarous faces of
                  <persName ref="#george_washington">Washington</persName> and <persName
                  ref="#thomas_jefferson">Jefferson</persName>, of <persName ref="#henry_clay"
                  >Clay</persName>, <persName ref="#daniel_webster">Webster</persName> and <persName
                  ref="#john_calhoun">Calhoun</persName>, present beside the fine expressive
               likeness of this rising little fellow. The American Nation, if it can, may try its
               hardened hand yet a few centuries longer upon our live little <persName
                  ref="thomas_onward">Tom</persName>; but it will hardly mould him to their liking.
               Like gold ore he will lose but the alloy and become brighter and brighter in the oft
               passing through the furnace of their oppression. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>PICTURE NO. XI.—THE BLACK FOREST.</head>
            <p>Two days after I had hung up the picture of the Gallery boy <persName
                  ref="thomas_onward">Tom</persName>, I sat examining another marked the <hi
                  rend="italic"><geogName>Black Forest</geogName></hi>, which from its grand and
               beautiful scenery, dark back ground shadows and the air of profound mystery which
               seemed to pervade it, so attracted me that I intended to make a sketch, but my mind
               turned towards the boy and my eyes towards the portrait, and I sat gazing upon its
               beauty, and meditating upon its superior excellence as a <hi rend="italic">Work of
                  Art</hi>, and the probable whereabouts of the unknown Artist, and also upon the
               destiny of the Boy himself, when his shrill, merry, musical voice rung out: <said>'a
                  letter sir.'</said>
            </p>
            <p>Taking it from his hand, I instantly broke the seal, and by a single glance
               discovered it was from an unknown source, and on further perusal that it was from the
                  <hi rend="italic"><geogName>Black Forest</geogName></hi>; a place and name then
               wholly unknown to me, except as the landscape painting just alluded to in the
               gallery. The purport of the letter was an invitation to visit this inhabited or
               uninhabited part of the globe. Let me give the reader one paragraph of this curious
               epistle. It ran thus: <hi rend="italic"><q>'Come over to the <geogName>Black
                        Forest</geogName> and examine some of the Pictures and other curiosities
                     there. Two days journey by stage and by foot for a man, and none others are
                     asked.'</q></hi> As it is no part of my purpose to disclose the precise
               locality of the Black <cb/>Forest, nor fully the manner of people dwelling there, nor
               yet wholly their doings, I shall reveal no more of the contents of this letter than
               to say it pointed out the route so minutely that no careful observer could mistake
               it; while without such a description, the keenest mind could not by any process
               penetrate even the recesses of the <geogName>Black Forest</geogName>, much less the
               precise spot in question. <q>'Come over to the <geogName>Black Forest</geogName> and
                  examine some of the Pictures and other curiosities there. Two days journey by
                  stage and by foot for a man, and none others are asked!'</q></p>
            <p>This paragraph I read over a dozen times ere I laid down the letter, and then all my
               old love of adventure, of ramble and of picture hunting came back upon me. </p>
            <p>Filled now with new thoughts and new projects, I repaired to my lodgings, wrote a few
               hasty lines to a friend, and retired for the night. But the sentences <q>'Come over
                  to the <geogName>Black Forest</geogName>. Examine some pictures and other
                  curiosities. Two days journey by stage and by foot for a man. None others are
                  asked,'</q> had fastened themselves in my mind and insisted so pertinaciously in
               remaining there, that it was with unusual effort sleep could take entire possession
               of me.</p>
            <p>Early next morning I commenced preparations for my journey, and my arrangements
               completed, I started on what to many might have seemed not only hazardous but
               profitless undertaking. But to him who bears perseverance about with him in his
               breast and determination in his face, and holds communion with all things around him,
               nothing is hazardous, nothing profitless. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>PICTURE NO. XII—TWO PORTRAITS THAT OUGHT TO BE HUNG UP. </head>
            <p>The forepart of my journey contained little of interest if I except the appearance
               and movements of two travellers whose portraits ought to be <pb n="102"/><cb/>hung up
               in our Gallery for the benefit of both Afric and Anglo American. </p>
            <p>One by one the stage emptied its passengers till these two individuals and myself
               only were left. Let me give a rough pencilling of each. One of them, and by far the
               most attractive of the pair, was a lean, sallow faced, lantern-jawed, hyena-looking
               little man, standing about four and a half feet in his boots, with a long, narrow,
               retreating forehead, heavy brow and small piercing black eyes and long black hair.
               His nervous excitability rose and fell with every jolt of the stage coach, and with
               every whiff of the wind. </p>
            <p>The other was an animal of yet a meaner cast. Though not a greyhound, nor a blood,
               still a kind of hound, a two legged one of a genuine American stock. </p>
            <p>He was large in frame and bloated in flesh. His hands resembled a pair of oyster
               rakes, and his feet shovels, such as are used by ditchers. Upon his large bullet
               head, which was closely cropped of its coarse bristly hair, jauntingly sat a low
               slouched hat, from beneath which his blood-shot eyes, when they dared to look
               directly at you, seemed truly terrible. His coarse, vulgar mouth contained a quid of
               tobacco nearly as large as your fist—genuine Virginian—the juice of which he squirted
               freely in all directions. His clothes were loose and slovenly, and his linen dirty.
               From his trouseers’ pocket obtruded a pair of shackles, from his vest a revolver, and
               from his inner shirt a dagger. </p>
            <p>Reader, here surely was a pair of portraits for you. I would have given half of all I
               ever possessed to have had these two rare specimens of Anglo humanity for our <hi
                  rend="quotes">Afric-American</hi> Gallery. I was certainly in a menagerie.</p>
            <p>They eyed me and I eyed them. Incidentally I learned that they were a <hi
                  rend="italic">Slave Holder</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">Slave Catcher</hi> in
               search of runaways, and mistook me for one. I prepared myself accord-<cb/>ingly, and
               should have made summary work with them, had a hand to hand encounter taken place,
               just such as fugitives should make in a like case. </p>
            <p>To assure themselves that their suspicions were correct, they struck up a
               conversation in good Old Virginia style, and I, willing to enliven or drive away I
               cared not which, the dull hours of the stage coach, readily joined in.</p>
            <p>They were not long in discovering not only their mistake but were soon routed. White
               men generally, and slave holders in particular dislike nothing so much as to stumble
               over and wake up black men capable of a single thought, much less intellectually
               equal, and none laugh more heartily than common sense black men over the extreme
               folly of the continually assumed or imagined mental superiority of white men over
               them. </p>
            <p>In this instance matters began to look quite serious, and I began to fear something
               more than a wordy encounter, as fingers began to twitch and pistols move from their
               places, but by dint of chewing and spitting and frothing and hard swearing and round
               ponderous oaths, affairs seemed their wonted state. But so chagrined were my
               companions at their sad discomfiture, that I verily believe had it been possible,
               they would have crawled into the harness of our horses and took their places if thus
               they could have passed from observation. </p>
            <p>Thus ended my first day’s journey towards the <geogName>Black Forest</geogName>. The
               second was to be mostly the pedestrian’s task. </p>
            <p>The stage coach sat me down by ten o’clock next morning, and my two companions eyed
               me so wistfully till the thick tangle wood separated us, that I was well satisfied
               that their desire to make me their prey was strong to the last. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>PICTURE NO. XIII.—A PICTURE OUTSIDE OF THE GALLERY</head>
            <p>Freed from this cage of wild beasts quite as miraculously as was Daniel <pb n="103"
               /><cb/> from the lion's den, I sat out in good earnest, and for a time made fine
               headway; a cold drizzling rain however sat in late in the day and the travel became
               bad. </p>
            <p>The afternoon wore away, and still I found myself wending towards a huge mountain
               forest, whose crest loomed up blacker and blacker as the clouds of coming evening
               rolled up from below the horizon. Here in all its grandeur and wild sublimity was the
               native landscape spread out before me, the same that I saw in beautiful miniature but
               a day before hanging on the walls of our Afric-American Gallery. Cold and wet, dark,
               gloomy night at last overtook me still plodding my weary way, now alas, through a
               dense and pathless forest in the direction of a solitary light. Dim at first, now
               brighter as I passed on and on.</p>
            <p>Three hours more gone, and now dancing still more brightly through the trees this
               solitary light to my unspeakable joy, suddenly revealed itself fully in a small open
               space, but almost as suddenly disappeared. </p>
            <p>A low growl of a mastiff told me that I was quite near the place of my search.
                  <said>Down, down sir!</said> said a gruff voice to the dog, and all was silent and
               dark as the grave. </p>
            <p>Used as I was to adventure and a stranger to fear, I confess a peculiar sensation now
               passed over me in this reign of deathlike stillness, and I for a moment hesitated.
                  <said>‘Men only are asked over to the <geogName>Black Forest</geogName>,'</said>
               whispered a still, small voice in my ear. </p>
            <p>I boldly stepped forward, and in a few moments came directly upon the steps of a
               small and unpretending log <hi rend="italic">hut</hi>. I lingered a moment on the
               landing; all was quiet within, but a gentle rap soon brought to the door a man who
               bade me enter. </p>
            <p>A cheerful wood fire was blazing on the open hearth, while three vacant chairs quite
               rural in aspect surround-<cb/>ed it, and a small table and an old fashioned settee
               completed the furniture of the apartment. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>PICTURE NO. XIV.--PORTRAIT OF A MAN. </head>
            <p>Tall and erect, strong like a forest tree, this man of the <placeName>Black
                  Forest</placeName>, for such he was, was a glory to look upon. The frost of at
               least ninety winters must have fallen upon his head, and yet had not chilled him, nor
               had their winds bowed him, nor their cold dimmed the fires of his eye. </p>
            <p>What a treasure, thought I, as I looked upon him, would this old man's portrait be in
               our Gallery. </p>
            <p><said>'From G—?'</said> said he, as he fixed his searching eyes upon me. I answered
               in the affirmative, and a brief but satisfactory conversation ensued. Mine host soon
               after set before me some cold meats, brown bread, an excellent dish of coffee and a
               bowl of delicious milk; thus with the aid of the cheerful fire, making me feel quite
               comfortable and at home, and the conversation was resumed. I shall not attempt even
               an outline of it. If I except my own part I could not if I would. </p>
            <p>I have listened to many men. It has long been my privilege to converse with men of
               intelligence, and men of mind on all topics common to the day, but never before did I
               wit ness such a flood of knowledge poured forth from the lips of man. I am no <hi
                  rend="italic">Paul</hi>, but surely I sat at the feet of <hi rend="italic"
                  >Gamaliel</hi>. Who was this man? How came he here? From whence did he come? What
               hidden treasures are there in this place? What mysteries hang over it? These
               interrogatories irresistably came up in my mind as the old man, with lamp in hand,
               began to ascend a rude ladder to a single upper chamber, bidding me follow. Here on a
               clean bed of rushes, I laid down, wondering at first, but soon buried myself in sound
               beneficial sleep. </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">(To be Continued.)</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <pb n="173"/>
            <dateline>JUNE 1859</dateline>
            <head>Afric-American Picture Gallery.—THIRD PAPER.</head>
            <byline>BY ETHI0P.</byline>
            <cb/>
            <p>The reader will remember, that we parted company in the upper chamber of a lone Hut,
               in the midst of the <geogName>Black Forest</geogName> at the dead of night to take
               rest and repose. Ere the dawn of the next day, both eyes were wide open and I started
               on a tour of observation. </p>
            <p>Through a small window, so high, as to be beyond reach, the only aperture discernable
               to the outer world, came a grey streak of morning light to my pillow, and roused me
               from my bed. I up and hastily made my toilet such as it was, the best perhaps that
               could be made in a mountain fastness, and ascended by a ladder to the roof. I shall
               never forget the scene that burst upon my view. The peak of the <geogName>Black
                  Forest</geogName> Mountain, for such it was upon which the solitary house stood,
               touched the very clouds, while the Ocean with here and there a massive ship upon its
               dark green bosom, though many miles distant, seemed to roll at its base. Crag on crag
               lay piled on every hand and vale outstretching vale; and beyond as it was early
               autumn, the sere and yellow leaf painted the otherwise vast green forest top with
               indescribable beauty. The morning breeze with a purity and freshness known only to
               mountain regions, sighed forth its soft music, so sweetly, that the feathered tribe,
               and they were legion—were constrained to join in with their unerring notes; while the
               deer, the squirrel, and the rabbit danced and skipped o'er steppe, crag and glen with
               laughing joy. A few moments, and the sun, like a mighty an gel came hastening up, as
               it were, from out of the Ocean; and with his strong presence gilded the whole scene
               in an instant. So, impressed with what I saw, ere I was aware, a reverie stole over
               me; and I know not how long it would have held me, but for a voice from below,
               calling me away. It was the old man of the Forest summoning <cb/> me to the morning
               repast; which to be brief, was all the most fastidious taste could have desired, and
               far be yond any thing I could have imagined.</p>
            <p>Breakfast over, the old man <hi rend="italic"><persName ref="#bernice"
                     >Bernice</persName></hi>, for such was his name, retired; but returned after a
               few moments, garbed in a red flannel gown, blue cap and black sandals; giving a
               grotesque, yet a most commanding appearance. Holding in his hand a lighted lantern,
               he advanced and mildly said; now my son, if you like, you may accompany me. So saying
               he led the way through a narrow passage to what appeared from the house top, a mere
               adjacent outbuilding. A stranger might have passed through this passage a thou sand
               times without so much as imagining that the huge rough stone laying almost in his
               pathway covered the mouth of a famous cave. </p>
            <p>At a slight touch from the old man's hand this stone rolled away as if by magic, and
               revealed a deep, dark <hi rend="italic">Cavern</hi>. With a firm step he began to
               descend a ladder and I followed. Down, down, down we went. Down, down, down; and long
               was it ere we reached the bottom; and when we did so, we were brought directly upon a
               massive door which like the stone above, yielded to the touch of the old man's magic
               hand. We entered a dark and spacious apartment through which old Bernice grouped to
               the centre and held the lighted lantern up to a large lamp which depended from the
               ceiling. What a transition!!! The dark and sandless cavern now revealed all
               surroundings of the most studied and life long <hi rend="italic">Artist</hi>. Bust,
               statues, statuettes; landscapes, portraits, fancy pieces; paints, pencils, pallets,
               mallets, chisels; half finished sketches, studies in plaster; all, all lay in
               profusion on every hand.</p>
            <p>Prominent on a table near the lamp lay a fine duplicate portrait of our lit-<pb
                  n="174" rend="wordbreaking"/><cb/> tle <hi rend="italic"><persName
                     ref="thomas_onward">Tom</persName></hi>; our Gallery Boy, which I hung up just
               before I left for the <hi rend="italic"><geogName>Black Forest</geogName></hi>. The
               whole truth flashed upon my mind in an instant. Mine host was an <hi rend="italic"
                  >Artist</hi>; and the executor of that beautiful likeness. <said>"My son"</said>
               said the old man as he perceived my astonishment, <said>"though I have long since
                  left the restless, busy crowd, I have not been unmindful of its jostlings. In this
                  place, far from man's baseness, and man's vile injustice, have I labored; and it
                  has been to me, a labor of love ; a labor too, not without its reward. Much that I
                  have done with both <hi rend="italic">pencil</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                     >chisel</hi>—(I say it not in a boastful spirit,) will yet not only see the
                  light, but command the just approbation of even the enemies of my race. I shall be
                  gone, but these,"</said> said he, pointing to his works around him, <said>"these
                  shall live after me."</said></p>
            <p>He then seated himself before his <hi rend="italic">Easel</hi>, stretched his
               canvass, and with brush and pallet commenced the labors of the day;—saying at the
               same time in a manner as bland as it was touching— <said>“Oblige me my son and amuse
                  also yourself by an examination of some of these my much <hi rend="italic"
                     >cherished creations</hi> trifles—many of them— still I regard them with the
                  affection of children.</said></p>
            <p><said>Some of them recall to mind some of the dearest spots of earth to me; spots,
                  which, if not for them, would long since have faded from my memory."</said> I soon
               entered upon my survey; and for the hours,—(and how swiftly did they fly,)—that the
               old man plied at his <hi rend="italic">work</hi> I reveled and feasted my mind upon
               the splendours about me.</p>
            <p>Here I found a statue or there a bust that might have done credit to the conception
               of a <hi rend="italic">Canova</hi> or the hand of an Angelo. </p>
            <p>Here hung a landscape, or half concealed, there lay a portrait or a Scripture piece
               or fancy sketch, that might have excited the envy of a <hi rend="italic"
               >Raphael</hi>. </p>
            <p>Among other things, my attention was arrested by a new curiosity. It was a <hi
                  rend="italic">Tablet</hi> of stone which mine host <cb/>informed me was dug out of
               the mountain peak of the <hi rend="italic"><geogName>Black Forest</geogName></hi>,
               but disclaimed all further knowledge of it. It is of brown sand stone, thirty-six
               inches square, and three in thickness, engraved on one side only; and having when
               found the engraved side downward.</p>
            <p>The words are curiously spelt by the aid of 41 singular, new and beautiful
               characters, or letters, each representing a distinct sound; and so many only are
               employed as are necessary to make up each word.</p>
            <p>I have by dint of hard study, been enabled to make out its contents; but of its
               history or origin, or aught else of it, I leave for the learned in such matters. It
               certainly challenges the attention of the Historian, the Ethnologist, and the
               Antiquarian. Is it fiction, is it history, is it prophecy? Who can tell? I herewith
               present a duplicate of the copy I made on the spot. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>YEAR 4,000.</head>
            <head>THE AMECANS, OR MILK WHITE RACE</head>
            <p>1. Now hear oh ye who dwell in this age of pure light and perfect liberty; and marvel
               not when I tell you that there were once such things as slaves in the land; since
               even the word slave is no more mentioned among the children of men. </p>
            <p>2. And these same slaves were human beings held in bondage—yea cruel bondage, against
               their will, and against the dictates of common humanity; and were subject to purchase
               and sale, like unto beast of burden and like unto merchandise. </p>
            <p>3. Nor marvel not that these slaves were whipped with great gads, and were driven to
               and fro in gangs and in chains, as we read of in our books, the beast of burden were
               in the <hi rend="italic">nineteenth and twentieth centuries</hi>; yea they were
               whipped often without offense even unto death. </p>
            <p>4. And be ye not puffed up nor proud in spirit, oh ye sons of noble fathers because
               ye now possess the land; and oh ye beautiful and refined <pb n="175"/><cb/>daughters
               of virtuous mothers, be ye not vain overmuch because this land is now yours for an
               inheritance for ever. </p>
            <p>5. Nor be ye enraged, none of yon, because ye hereby learn that your <hi
                  rend="italic">ancestors</hi> were these slaves, and subject to this hard bondage. </p>
            <p>6. And give ye heed now while from this Tablet of stone, which your fathers made;
               [and other tablets have they made also] I speak to you, and tell you what manner of
               people possessed the land and bought and sold and held your ancestors and so
               despitefully used them. </p>
            <p>7. And lo and behold, as one appeared, so appeared all of them. They had <hi
                  rend="italic">milk white shins</hi>, and their faces were like the chalk of
               foreign hills, yea like unto the evil spirit; and their hair was long and strait and
               uncomely; and in hue as the yellow or red clay of our fields. </p>
            <p>8. And their faces were long and narrow, and their noses sharp and angular, and their
               nostrils thin; so also were the lips of their sunken mouths, </p>
            <p>9. They had sharp white teeth, like unto the teeth of the shark; and their eyes were
               blue as the cloudless sky, and sometimes leaden as when it is overcast; and their
               brows were large even unto the hiding of their eyes; and they were terrible to look
               upon, yea even fearful. </p>
            <p>10. And these people, long ruled in the land, and their hand was the the hand of
               iron, and their hearts as the stones of our valleys.</p>
            <p>11. And though they had great energy, and their wills were like unto the oaks of our
               forest, their unscrupulousness was great, yea as huge as our mountains; and their
               consciences were less than a span and harder than the diamond. </p>
            <p>12. They built them large cities, and made great attainments in <hi rend="italic"
                  >science</hi> and in <hi rend="italic">art</hi>; and were cunning workmen, and
               wonderful tillers of the soil, making it yield its abundance. </p>
            <p>13. And they made them great <hi rend="italic">ships</hi> and many; so much so, that
               <cb/>the seas were whitened with their sails; and they sent great burdens out of
               their land; and they got in return great riches. </p>
            <p>14. And they builded also gorgeous <hi rend="italic">temples</hi> in which they
               worshipped the <hi rend="italic">Gods</hi> of their own making, while they professed
               to worship the true <hi rend="italic">God</hi>; all of whose known laws they
               violated, and did but evil in his sight daily. </p>
            <p>15. And your forefathers, they would not so much as permit them to enter the seats of
               their <hi rend="italic">temples</hi> though they worshipped the true God, nor at
               their solemn feasts; but compelled them to stand afar off, because they had great
               hatred and prejudice against your forefathers. </p>
            <p>16. And this people waxed fat and begat great pride, and clothed themselves in fine
               linen and black cloth every day; and their hearts be came more and more filled with
               the world and the lust thereof. </p>
            <p>17. And they said, who is like unto us? We are the great and the mighty ones of the
               Earth, and have a great mission to perform. We will level the hills and fill up the
               vallies; and will lay the mountains low, and make the path of the land straight, and
               they did so. </p>
            <p>18. And we will lay on the path iron of our own workmanship and swift running
               vehicles will we put thereon, so that when the warm breath of the water puffeth at
               them they will run with swiftness and we will add to our cities and increase our
               comforts; and they did so. </p>
            <p>19. And they wrapped themselves up in their ease and luxury in hopeful security; and
               their hand slackened; and great physical and mental weakness came over them ; and
               many changes came in among them; so much so, that your forefathers looked upon them
               with much concern. </p>
            <p>20. Yea their hair darkened, so also did their eyes and their skins; and they said
               unto your forefathers let us come in among you and be of you and partake of your
               substance les: before our time.</p>
            <pb n="176"/>
            <p>21. And your forefathers did so; for they had increased much in sub stance and in
               numbers; and much in strength and in wisdom also ; and had gained great possessions,
               yea all the land.</p>
            <p>22. And these people dwindled at last to leanness; and their bones be came small, and
               thin, and so did their statues; and their minds became feeble, so much so, that they
               wist not what they did; and finally they disappeared from among the children of men. </p>
            <p>23. They staid no longer than to accomplish their <hi rend="italic">work</hi> and
               then vanished; yea as a cloud did they vanish from off the face of the whole land;
               yea the land which your fathers have since possessed and enjoyed. </p>
            <p>24. And it is a great grief unto this day that so little, beyond these <hi
                  rend="italic">tablets</hi> of stone, your fathers have left unto you that so
               little is now known of these <hi rend="italic">Amecans</hi> or that a people once
               possessing so many peculiar traits, should have passed away without leaving to your
               fathers some greater memortal of their existence. </p>
            <p>25. But <hi rend="italic">wo</hi> was unto the ; and their works with their evil
               deeds seem to have perished with them.' </p>
            <p>Simultaneous with my finishing this transcript, old Bernice rose from his labors. He
               lighted his lantern and saying 'come my son,' stepped to a side door hitherto
               unperceived by me but which like the first instantly yielded to his touch. We now
               turned into a narrow passage and continued in its subterraneous windings some fifty
               yards to another massive door, wdiich like others swung back at the old mans bidding.
               But what a change ! ! ! </p>
            <p>From the artistic, the beautiful and the curious, we had just quitted, an object the
               most appalling my eyes ever beheld stood before us. Was it a man, was it even human?—
               When we entered he stood crouched in one corner of his cell. His figure was gaunt and
               tall; his head large and covered with long snow white hair, which hung in disordered
               masses over his pale and shriveled face; and through which <cb/> his glaring eyes
               kept up a most terrible rolling; while his mouth was white with foam. He soon
               commenced an incoherent muttering the only word's distinguishable was <said><hi
                     rend="italic"><persName ref="#bernice">Bernice</persName>, Bernice!</hi></said>
            </p>
            <p>Suddenly he made a fearful lunge for me. I started back. It was a useless start. A
               chain was there. He could go no further. Then he raved, he shrieked, he tore his
               hair; then he pronounced the most awful imprecations upon his captor, upon all man
               kind, upon his <hi rend="italic">Maker</hi>; then he sub sided into the same low and
               unintelligent murmur again, <hi rend="italic"><persName ref="#bernice"
                     >Bernice</persName></hi> being the only distinguishable word. </p>
            <p>Suddenly he knelt; then he prayed; then he sprang up, then he bounded the length of
               his chains, then he stamped them in the earth, then he gnawed at their links; then he
               begged, then he pled incoherently for something; I thought it was for deliverance and
               instinctively stepped forward as though to give it. <said><hi rend="italic">Stay !
                     !</hi></said> commanded <hi rend="italic">Old Bernice</hi> in voice that I
               shall never forget." A stout heart only saved me from immediate petrification on the
               spot; and when my eyes met his I confess I had some misgivings as to my own safety.
               And where fore this man, said I.</p>
            <p><said>‘This man! he is a murderer'</said> said he; and the old man's eyes kindled
               almost to a living flame. <said>'He is a murderer!!'</said> exclaimed he again. </p>
            <p>
               <said>'The wretch once had wealth and ad the influence it brings; he once hall power
                  and he exercised it like a fiend. The oppressed and helpless were the victims of
                  his fiendish spirit. Many, too many of God's poor have, alas, felt his diabolical
                  hand, <hi rend="italic">I</hi> was one of his victims, and dearly, dearly have I
                  paid the cost. I had a wife and children.</said>
            </p>
            <p>
               <said>‘He held them as his property. Would you ask the fiend where they now are; or
                  shall the sigh of the winds as they come up from the rice swamps answer? I had a
                  son, a son dear to me, though he held him too as property. Despite oppression he
                  had grown to beautiful manhood.</said>
            </p>
            <pb n="177"/>
            <cb/>
            <p><said>Would you ask him where that son now is? Shall I answer that? Listen ! That
                  chained hand the wretch now lifts toward heaven and yon for undeserved mercy, that
                  chained hand struck down that son to the earth ; and with that other hand withered
                  as you see it, the wretch blew out the brains of my child without provocation and
                  without warning; and would not so much as allow his body burial.'</said> The old
               man made a pause, and I took advantage of it and said something about the law,
               redress, justice &amp;c. <said><hi rend="italic">'Laws!'</hi></said> exclaimed he
               almost frantic. <said>'<hi rend="italic">Laws ! !</hi> what laws, what justice is
                  there for the oppressed of our <hi rend="italic">class</hi>? What laws except to
                  oppress them harder? What laws except to pursue and rob them from the cradle to
                  the grave, yea even beyond both. The wretch there,'</said> said he pointing more
               significantly than ever at the miserable object before us, <said>'the wretch opulent
                  in lands, opulent in human chattels, received the general approbation of his
                  associate Tyrants for his <hi rend="italic">acts</hi>.'</said></p>
            <p><said>‘But no matter,'</said> continued he, <said>'I made my resolve and came hither.
                  An interval was permitted to pass—a short one. He was brought hither, by what
                  means I need not say. He was placed in my power. We confronted each other. It was
                  a sore trial to him. We conversed much and freely. He spoke of the wrong done him;
                  I spoke of mine. He spoke of his wife and children left behind. I reminded him of
                  the sale and separation of mine. He spoke of his position in society and the wide
                  difference between us. I told him that his superior advantage and position, so far
                  from making him a wiser, and better man, had availed him little, worse than
                  little, since it had made him a robber of the helpless, an oppressor of the weak
                  and a murderer of the innocent. He plead earnestly for his rights. I told him he
                  had no rights that I was bound to respect. He then begged hard for his liberty. It
                  was a strange sight,'</said> said he, <said>'to see a <cb/> man begging for
                  liberty from one of a class of whom he had his whole life long deprived of not
                  only liberty but all that makes life worth having. He made large promises for that
                  liberty. I told him that they were useless that he had now nothing to give; that
                  he no longer possessed even himself; that his pleadings were now as useless as
                  mine once were; that I was now the master and he the slave. I then as signed him
                  his fate, and bid him prepare to meet it.</said>
            </p>
            <p>
               <said>Long years have since gone by. I yet have him in my possession. I will not harm
                  a hair of his head; but so long as he lives that gloomy cell shall be his
                  prison-house, and these chains he is now bearing about with him in his sleeping
                  moments and in last long waking hours, shall be his only earthly companions ; and
                  when he dies, as die he must, I will cast his carcass forth to gorge the <hi
                     rend="italic">Vultures</hi> that sit upon the mountain peaks of the
                     <geogName>Black Forest</geogName>.'</said>
            </p>
            <p><said>'<persName ref="#bernice">Bernice</persName>, Bernice,'</said> imploringly
               murmured this white trembling <hi rend="italic">Felix</hi>; and his knees smote
               together with very fear, as he stood before his <hi rend="italic">sable master</hi>
               and heard his words.</p>
            <p>The huge drops of perspiration rolled down my face as I said to myself what a
               terrible fate for a once proud tyrannical, wealthy white man who regards the black
               man as but a poor imbecile ignorant feeble thing, not so much even as the beasts that
               perish. </p>
            <p>As the wretched fiend, for such I too now, regarded him, commenced again his wild and
               loud imprecations, so loud that it seemed like a thousand voices, old Bernice drew
               himself up to his full height, and with a commanding gesture waved me to retire, and
               following said <said>'my son, thou hast as yet seen but little of this place;'</said>
               and then turning round with one touch of his hand the heavy door sprang back to its
               place, and all sounds within that cell were hushed from the <hi rend="italic"
                  >world</hi>.</p>
            <p>(<hi rend="italic">To be Continued.</hi>)</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <pb n="216"/>
            <dateline>JULY 1859</dateline>
            <head>Afric-American Picture Gallery. FIFTH PAPER </head>
            <byline>BY ETHIOP</byline>
            <cb/>
            <epigraph>
               <lg>
                  <l>—Home again, and in fine spirits.</l>
                  <l>
                     <said>"Sound, sound the clarion, fill the fife ;</said>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <said>To all the sensual world proclaim,</said>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <said>One crowded hour of glorious life.</said>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <said>Is worth an age without a name."</said>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </epigraph>
            <p>So felt I, after my visit to the <geogName>Black Forest</geogName>, which has been
               among the most remarkable of my meandering life. A faithful recital of what I heard
               and what I saw, lengthened out in a dozen carefully collated and closely written
               volumes, would scarcely do justice to my three days' stay in that place of mysteries.
               But, as the pressure of other engagements called me from those never-to-be-forgotten
               scenes, so now, also, do the events of the passing hour require at my hands some
               thing else for my readers, reserving for another occasion a further chat about the
               famous Grotto Home of Old Bernice, one of Nature's noblemen and one of her noblest
               artists.</p>
            <p>Home again, and in the Afric-American <cb/>Picture Gallery, and seated in my big arm
               chair. Dear old arm-chair! seated in thee I survey with renewed and increasing
               satisfaction this extraordinary Gallery. </p>
            <p>My feelings are fresh and my eye clear, so that I can, perhaps, better take in the
               beauties and excellencies of a picture than give out anything like an accurate
               description of one.</p>
            <p>Notwithstanding this, I cannot resist the temptation of a sketch offered by a pair of
               pictures just beneath my eye. on the south side of the Gallery.</p>
            <p>They are marked </p>
            <p><title rend="italic">Pictures Nos. XIX and XX.</title> PREACHING AND AFTER
               PREACHING.</p>
            <p>The first represents the interior of a church—a negro church.</p>
            <p>Locality—sunny South. The particular spot, I conclude from its surroundings, is among
               the best of the good old plantations.</p>
            <p>The church is filled to overflowing with <cb/><pb n="217"/>devout worshippers, and is
               being discoursed to, affectionately, of course, by a double fisted, burly,
               white-faced old Southern Preacher—a genuine Hard Shell.</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="italic">artist</hi> has caught him just in the nick of time.</p>
            <p>The Preacher is just in the act of extorting his sable hearers to obey their
               masters—their kind, good masters.</p>
            <p><said>"He that knoweth his master's will and doeth it not shall be beaten with many
                  stripes."</said> These are his words. In catching the artist's conception, you
               feel them, you hear them—you put yourself in his audience, and then they are gracious
               words to you. They are unctious. On them your parson is feeling; he looks full of
               feeling; he looks unctious all over. Unction pours out of his mouth ; it beams out of
               his eyes ; it sticks out of his outspread fingers ; it runs down his broad face in
               greater profusion than did the oil down the venerable beard of Aaron. </p>
            <p>Just at this unctious point is our good man taken, and I heartily thank the artist
               for having done him such justice. A fairer exhibit of a Southern preacher is
               certainly nowhere else on canvass. </p>
            <p>Nor has the artist lost any of his inspiration in the other details of his picture.
               The preacher's sable hearers, with eyes dilated, mouths agape, nostrils distended and
               ears alert, are intently leaning forward, that they may lose no word of the good
               admonition, while here a moody brow, and there a skeptical face, or yonder a defiant
               look, combine to form an admirable background. </p>
            <p>The second of this pair of pictures, entitled <title rend="italic">After
                  Preaching</title>, represents the congregation standing about outside the church
               in groups around the faithful leaders, who, being men carefully selected by the white
               piety of the sunny South, are of course, all of the Uncle Tom school. </p>
            <p>By another masterly stroke of the artist's conception, they are taken just at the
               point of the extreme of their extacies about the great and good sermon they have just
               heard, while the leaders are in earnest exhortation on submission and willing
               obedience to masters as the height of Christian duty. </p>
            <p>In the background may also be seen a few young, determined-looking faces, on which
               are expressed disbelief in, and de testation of, the whole affair. They are <cb/>the
               same noticed in the back-ground of the former piece. </p>
            <p>These young spirit-faces possess such a strong look of meaning that none need mistake
               it. A look so strong, so bold, so towering, that, like Monadnoc among the granite
               hills, it peers far above the scrawny frowns, and puny smiles, and jeers, and gibes,
               and sneers, and hates of the vulgar, the mean, the base; a look that will go up
               through all time, and, as light before the coming sun, so as surely will it be the
               forerunner of the great deliverance of long-pressed humanity. The look and the
               meaning do actually exist, and the sooner the World knows it the better.</p>
            <p>These faces, in contrast with the others of the congregation, give a most striking
               effect to the picture. They are the unholy, the skeptical, the worthless of the
               flock—the wicked ones, who would rather run the risk than be bound up in the
               religious love so feelingly and so faithfully proclaimed to them—the religious love
               of the land. </p>
            <p>It is of this class comes our Nat Turners, who laid a scheme for redemption, and the
                  <hi rend="italic">man</hi> in Georgia who received nine hundred and ninety-nine
               lashes by way of gentle compulsion, and then would not so much as reveal one particle
               of the <hi rend="italic">plan</hi> laid by and for the uprising of his oppressed
               brethren. It is of this class come the Margaret Garners, who rather than their babes
               even shall clank a chain, prefer to send them up to their God who gave them. It is of
               this class comes our Douglasses and our Browns, and a host of other spirits now cast
               upon the regions of the North, as a Southern er once expressed it, <said>"to wailin
                  the misery of their sins, and lament in the wretched ness of their misunderstood
                  liberty."</said>
            </p>
            <p>These are good views, and may be studied with profit by any Southern Preacher, master
               or monster who will take the trouble to visit the Afric-American Picture Gallery.
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p><title rend="italic">Picture No. XXI.</title> is A HEAD OF <persName
                  ref="#phillis_wheatley">PHILLIS WHEATLY</persName>.</p>
            <p>It hangs in the north-east corner of the Gallery, and in good light, and is so
               decidedly one of the finest in the collection, whether viewed in an artistic light or
               in point of fact, that it is both a constant charm and study for me. The features,
               though indicative of a delicate organiza-<pb n="218" type="wordbreaking"/><cb/>tion,
               are of the most pleasing cast. The facial angle contains full ninety degrees; the
               forehead is finely formed, and the brain large ; the nose is long, and the nostrils
               thin, while the eyes, though not large, are well set. To this may be added a small
               mouth, with lips prettily turned, and a chin—that perfection of beauty in the female
               face—delicately tapered from a throat and neck that are of themselves perfection. The
               whole make-up of this face is an index of healthy intellectual powers, combined with
               an active temperament, over which has fallen a slight tinge of religious pensiveness.
               Thus hangs <persName ref="#phillis_wheatley">Phillis Wheatly</persName> before you in
               the Afric-American Picture Gallery, and if we scrutinize her more closely through her
               career and her <hi rend="italic">works</hi>, we shall find her truly an extraordinary
               person. Stolen at the tender age of seven years from the fond embraces of a mother
               whose image never once faded from her memory, and ferried over in the <hi
                  rend="italic">vile slave ship</hi> from <placeName>Afric</placeName>'s sunny clime
               to the cold shores of <placeName>America</placeName>, and sold under the hammer to a
               Boston merchant—a delicate child, a girl, alone, desolate; a chilly, dreary world
               before her, a chain on her feet and a thorn in her bosom, and an iron mask on her
               head, what chance, what opportunity was there for her to make physical, moral, or
               mental progress? In these respects, how get up to, or keep pace with, other and more
               favored people?—how get in the advance?—how ascend, at last, without a single
               competitor, the highest scale of human eminence? <persName ref="#phillis_wheatley"
                  >Phillis Wheatly</persName> did all and more than this. A sold thing, a bought
               chattel, at seven years she mastered, notwithstanding, the English language in
               sixteen months. She carried on with her friends and acquaintances an extensive and
               elegant epistolary correspondence at twelve years of age, composed her first poem at
                  <hi rend="italic">fourteen</hi>, became a proficient Latin scholar at <hi
                  rend="italic">seventeen</hi>, and published in England her book of poems dedicated
               to the <persName ref="#selena_hastings">Countess of Huntington</persName> at <hi
                  rend="italic">nineteen</hi>; and with the mantle of just fame upon her shoulders,
               sailed from <placeName>America</placeName> to <placeName>England</placeName> to
               receive the meed due to her learning, her talents, and her virtues at twenty-two.
               What one of America's paler daughters cotemporary with her, with all the advantages
               that home, fortune, friends and favor bring—what one ascended so far up the hill of
               just fame at any age. I have searched <cb/>in vain to find the name upon the literary
               page of our country's record. </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Oh! Wheatly!</l>
               <l>What degrading hand, what slavish chain. </l>
               <l>What earthly power could link thy nobler soul </l>
               <l>To baser things, and check its eagle flight </l>
               <l>Angel of purity, child of beauteous song, </l>
               <l>Thy harp still hangs within our sight </l>
               <l>To cheer though thou art gone. </l>
            </lg>
            <p>The lady visitors to the Gallery would do well to make the head of <persName
                  ref="#phillis_wheatley">Phillis Wheatly</persName> a study. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <p>I have never read a <hi rend="italic">treatise</hi> on the art of pleasing, nor have
               I otherwise acquired it, and hence my imperfection in so important a matter. I never
               could well please; a lady friend says I have never tried. Be this as it may, permit
               me to observe that since my three days' visit to the <placeName>Black
                  Forest</placeName> and three weeks' barricading of the doors of the Afric-American
               Picture Gallery against its many friends who have sought it out, there has been
               brought upon me such a storm of choleric feeling as will serve for all of life to
               come. I had just finished the last sketch, and wrapped myself up in the happy
               consciousness of its justness, my old mood stealing over me, my mind traversing back
               to the days when Banneker lived and told of the stars and of the rising suns, and
                  <persName ref="#phillis_wheatley">Wheatly</persName> sung their praise to
               listening worlds, when a loud rap at the door brought me to a sense of the present
               moment and to my feet. Wondering who the intruder might be that dared to thus disturb
               me, I bade him enter. It was <hi rend="italic">Tom</hi>—yes, Tom, with a package of
               letters in his hand. The little rogue's smile was as fresh and sunny as ever, and it
               was a pleasure to see him ; but, somehow or other, there was a wicked twinkle playing
               about the corners of his usually wicked little eyes, that told me something in my
               absence had gone amiss. I concealed this discovery, however, and merely said:
                  <said>"Well, <persName ref="#thomas_onward">Tom</persName>, my good fellow, what
                  has turned up since my absence?"</said>
               <said>" Oh! nothing much, only a plenty of calls, sir,"</said> said he.
                  <said>"Calls?"</said> said I, rising, <said>"I hope you have not permitted, sir,
                  any one to enter the Afric American Gallery during my absence?”</said>
               <said>"Why no, sir,"</said> said he, provokingly, <said>"but then there has been such
                  a knocking at the door!"</said></p>
            <pb n="219"/>
            <cb/>
            <p>I perceived how it was in an instant. The little rogue had been operating on his own
               hook, and pointing out the Gallery to the various magnates around for his own special
               amusement. </p>
            <p><said>“The doctor has been here,"</said> he added, without paying any heed to the
               embarrassment in which he had placed me ; <said>"and the Professor has been here, and
                  the Philosopher with him ; and a little lady in black, and a tall lady, and a fat
                  lady, and a strange nice lady from abroad have been here ; and a number of other
                  ladies, and some queer ones, too, have been here ; and a crusty old gentleman,
                  (white,) with a cane, has been here, too ; and two colored gentlemen, in white
                  cravats and long black coats all buttoned down before."</said></p>
            <p>Tom's odd description of so strange a group really put me in good humor. I took the
               package from his hand, and throwing it on the table, wheeled round <cb/> before the
               stature of <persName ref="#benjamin_banneker">Benjamin Banneker</persName>, for the
               purpose of a few <hi rend="italic">notes</hi> for the readers of the <title
                  rend="italic">Anglo-African Magazine</title>, when rather a loud and unusual noise
               in the out er hall interrupted me. In looking up, lo ! and behold, advancing and
               bowing, hats in hand, who should my eyes meet but the <hi rend="italic">Doctor</hi>,
               the <hi rend="italic">Professor</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">Philosopher</hi>,
               closely followed by the little lady in black, and the tall lady, and the fat lady,
               and the lady from abroad, and the two gentle men in white cravats and long black
               coats all buttoned down before, fetching up the rear. Dumbfounded at so many and such
               imposing visitors, I could only rise and make my best bow, which was awkward enough
               at best. Of course I was cheated out of my reflections on <persName
                  ref="#benjamin_banneker">Banneker</persName>, and so are my readers.</p>
            <p>The conversation of my visitors, which was free, characteristic, and remarkable, I
               must reserve for my next, reader.</p>

            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">(To be Continued.)</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <pb n="243"/>
            <dateline> AUG 1859</dateline>
            <head>Afric-American Picture Gallery.</head>
            <head>SIXTH PAPER.</head>
            <byline>BY ETHI0P.</byline>
            <p>It may not be forgotten by the reader, that I was last seen standing bolt-upright in
               the middle of the Afric-American Picture Gallery, surrounded by quite a number of the
               notables of our times, who had been attracted thither by the notoriety the Gallery
               has recently assumed. </p>
            <p><said>"What a singular picture,"</said> exclaimed the little lady in black as she
               fixed her attention upon a small picture just opposite. This, to my own relief, drew
               the attention of the entire party. <said>"It is singularly sad, even distressingly
                  so,"</said> said the "lady from abroad;" <said>"and yet,"</said> she added,
                  <said>"it is susceptible of improvement. Such a condition, though it tax our best
                  energies, should be rendered better."</said>
               <said>"I much doubt, if such a sorry subject as that could be improved in
                  condition,"</said> broke in the "tall [not fat] lady." [Anglo-African Magazine
               must father that appellation.] This last remark was backed up by the "stout lady,"
               who always seemed but a necessary prop to the tall one—seemed made stout and strong,
               and short and broad, for that very purpose.</p>
            <p>That the reader may better appreciate these remarks, I will here give a simple <cb/>
               outline of the picture to which they had reference. </p>
            <p>It is marked "<title rend="quotes"><hi rend="italic">Picture</hi> 26,</title>" hangs
               on the North wall of the Gallery, and is entitled "<title rend="quotes"
                  >Condition.</title>" The subject is a <hi rend="italic">colored youth</hi>,
               sitting upon the bank of a rapid river, beneath a huge tree much resembling the upas,
               and surrounded by abject wretchedness. Rags and their concomitants cover his body;
               poverty and want stare him in the face, a face marked with ignorance and the in
               difference of stolid content.</p>
            <p>All else is vacancy.—Pale and emaciated he sits; and at this vacancy alone he stares.
               What the amount of intelligence he has, or what he is capable of acquiring, is for
               the speculative, the philosophic and philanthropic to ascertain. On the opposite bank
               of this river however, are green pastures, lowing herds and waving corn; while down
               the swift-gliding stream, are miniature fleets of heavy laden little skiffs and
               beautiful pleasure-yachts. The artist may be forgiven for over-drawing occasionally,
               as in the case of the main subject of this picture; for I am sure, it would be
               difficult to find within the whole range of our know-<pb n="244" type="wordbreaking"/>
               <cb/>ledge anything reduced to a condition com pared with it.</p>
            <p>And yet the question put by the "tall lady" and backed up by the "stout lady," and
               oft repeated on the tongue of nearly all Anglo-Americans: <said>"can such a subject
                  be improved?"</said> incidentally received a partial discussion, if not solution,
               in our Gallery. The Doctor, who is a piece of a philosopher and a larger bit of a
               wag, was intent on a fine large picture of the <title rend="italic">"First Colored
                  Convention;"</title> and, overhearing the conversation as above noted down, turned
               round to the company. <said>"What do you think of that, Doctor,"</said> asked a dozen
               voices together; pointing to poor little "<title rend="italic">Condition</title>" on
               the wall. The Doctor, after a few hurried glances at the picture through his <hi
                  rend="italic">turtle shells</hi>, said, <said>"you may improve the condition, if
                  you change the nature."</said>
            </p>
            <p>An opinion—though it meant nothing—from so high an authority, and so deliberately
               given, was not without its weight; and the "Skeptic" shook his head doubtingly; while
               the "Philosopher" with thumb and finger, and outstretched hand, launched out on
               hair-splitting subtleties, to prove the amount of labor necessary to make even the
               "Doctor's" proposition good. He also entered upon a learned dissertation, upon the
               nature of the world in general, and our <hi rend="italic">poor little
                     "<title>Condition</title>" in particular</hi>; and wound up by saying that
                  <said>"whatever is, is right."</said>
            </p>
            <p>All this to me seemed so foreign from the point at issue, that, my impetuosity
               getting the better of my known modesty, with arm uplifted and fist clenched, I broke
               out with: <said>"It is the youth's condition, not his nature, that demands a change.
                  He has all the great essentials common to humanity; hence, he neither wants more
                  of this, nor less of that, within his composition, before he can be rendered
                  susceptible of improvement."</said>
               <said>"Will our Gallery-friend inform us then, how he would effect that
                  change,"</said> enquired one of the "white cravats," who had all this time been
               balancing like a rope-dancer, first on this side, and then on that—of the rail of the
               conversation—to see which would best bear him. <said>"How would you proceed in so
                  great an undertaking,"</said> said he, and concluded his own effort, by drawing
               himself up in an attempt to look dignified. <said>"Put a lever in his hands, and he
                  will proceed to raise himself from out of his own low Condition,"</said> said the
               "Philosopher."</p>
            <cb/>
            <p>This was not quite definite enough, and the "skeptic" added, <said>"if the
                  Philosopher will compose his <hi rend="italic">lever</hi> of <hi rend="italic"
                     >means</hi> and <hi rend="italic">intelligence</hi>, I will agree with him. The
                  youth wants first of all things, means, substantial means—wealth; such as the
                  world values, and then intelligence enough to use it, and a fig for either his
                  dull eye, his curly hair, or his <hi rend="italic">ebon face</hi>.—The most
                  repulsive of his features may laugh in derision at their sternest foe; for they
                  will appear charming to the surrounding crowd, their possessor's friends. Beauty's
                  eyes are wealth and power."</said></p>
            <p><said>"I now perceive the point of the argument,"</said> chimed in one of the long
               black coats; and he buttoned it all down before. <said>"It is the youth's
                  disabilities, and not his color, that bind him there;"</said> and as he said this,
               he significantly pointed to the picture with his ram's-horn cane, strongly reminding
               one of ancient Jericho and its falling walls. <said>"Precisely so,"</said> said I;
                  <said>"you have it at last."</said> Notwithstanding I thought him very slow to
               perceive a plain point, and came near telling him so.</p>
            <p>At this point the "lady from abroad" mildly interposed, and said: <said>"take that
                  youth, forlorn and wretched even, as you there behold him; and let but the light
                  of culture beam in upon him, change not his physical, but his moral, mental and
                  religious state ; and then possess him with <hi rend="italic">means</hi>—<hi
                     rend="italic">with wealth;</hi> and you place beneath him a power, and put in
                  his hands a force, that will be felt throughout the entire ramifications of human
                  society."</said></p>
            <p>This lady had such a neat way of putting her propositions, that it was not an easy
               task to disturb them without risk; and so the "Doctor," the "Philosopher" and the
               "white Cravats and long black Coats" deemed it best to keep quiet; but an old lady,
               who had hitherto been a quiet spectator to the whole scene, now threw up her <hi
                  rend="italic">spectacles</hi>, and sharply remarked; <said>"you young folks' talk
                  is altogether too metaphorical for me, as my good brother—>a Philosopher,—yes, a
                  Philosopher of the old school—a real Philosopher—used to say, when he overheard
                  folks (he did not wish to offend), who did not know exactly what they were talking
                  about. He always said to them, "you speak too metaphorically for me, "and so say I
                  to you, my young friends."</said>
               <said>"You are not understood"</said> ejaculated the old lady quite out of breath.
               She then drew her shawl a <pb n="245"/><cb/>little closer, tossed back her hat,
               adjusted her specs, and began an examination of the picture in question, as she
               thought; but which was in fact one entitled <title>"Farm Life in Western
                  America."</title></p>
            <p>The whole Party, which for the moment was put to silence, at this unexpected sally,
               stood a picture of suppressed mirth and hilarity, as they observed the "old lady's"
               careful scrutiny of what she believed to be the subject of their conversation.
                  <said>"Bless me,"</said> said she at length; <said>"what is this? Colored folks
                  farming!! Ah now, that is it. This puts the question in a clear light; and if you
                  young folks could only throw up your metaphorical veils, you could see it."</said>
            </p>
            <p>No one ventured to interrupt, and she proceeded: <said>"Now here are colored folks
                  farming for themselves ; and don't their grain grow as well as if they were white
                  ; and don't it sell as well ?"</said>
            </p>
            <p><said>"Is not this a change only of condition? Talk of changing nature !!!</said>" </p>
            <p><said>"But where is the boy, that I hear you say so much about,"</said> inquired the
               "old lady," evidently puzzled.—<said>“The Village?"</said> said she. <said>"Yes, yes
                  ; and here is its colored village blacksmith, shoeing his white neighbor's
                  horse."</said>—<said>“What can't change our condition?"</said></p>
            <p><said>"Fiddle-sticks and nonsense,"</said> exclaimed she again. <said>"Talk of
                  changing appearances !"</said></p>
            <p><said>"And look here,"</said> cried she out again ; <said>"here is a colored man
                  tending his own mill; and is not the flour as white as any other ? and are not all
                  the town, white and colored, running to procure it?"</said>
            </p>
            <p><said>"Welladay, welladay,"</said> said the "old lady," and shook her head
               disapprovingly. Peering over the picture, she spied a splendid carriage, drawn by a
               span of spanking bays, driven by a boy, and containing the owner, a colored gentleman
               and his family, just entering the village.</p>
            <p><said>“The Lord be praised,”</said> fairly screamed out the “old lady” this time; and
               she put up both hands, threw up her specs, and wheeled square round to the company,
               exclaiming : <said>"and you would have them change the color of their faces, would
                  you, before you would have them ride thus ? This is your methaphysics, is
                  it?"</said> and <said>"welladay, welladay,"</said> muttered she again.</p>
            <p>A little farther on, and she espied a large <cb/>mansion, in process of erection by
               colored, and white mechanics conjointly. </p>
            <p><said>"The Lord be praised,"</said> ejaculated she again. <said>"Now if this is not,
                  what I call truly practical. For it is truly a practical operation where color is
                  no bar,"</said> said the old lady. <said>—Away with your methaphorical,
                  methaphysical nonsense, and give them plenty of the wherewith to do with, and they
                  may wear their color without let or hindrance."</said> And as if doubly to assure
               herself and the company of the correctness of her opinion, she re-affirmed it, by
               saying, <said>"possess them, all round, with money and all its pertainances; and no
                  station is there so high and no power so great, but will, at their pleasure, be
                  handed down to them."</said> The "Doctor," whom the "old lady" eyed with a
               keenness evidently provoking retort, dared venture no reply, and only bit his lips.
               One of the "White Cravats" buttoned down his coat, elongated his face, and poised
               himself on both sides of the argument, manifestly anxious—since the "Doctor" said
               nothing—to jump down on the "old lady's' side of the argument; while the other "long
               black Coat" pulled up his cravat, and enjoyed vastly his friend's vacillating but
               uneasy position. The "little woman in black seemed" quite self-satisfied, that she
               had called attention to so grave a subject; for gravity and weight were her themes,
               her elements, her life, her all. In them she lived, moved and had her being. </p>
            <p>The "tall lady" failed to see any convincing proofs; and so did the "stout lady," her
               friend and necessary prop. </p>
            <p>The "Philosopher" archly enquired if the ladies saw at all?—</p>
            <p>At this the "tall lady" grew taller, and the "stout lady" stouter; so much so, that I
               began to get anxious for the unfortunate "philosopher," and midly suggested that the
               ladies would find some interesting views on the other side of the Gallery. The
               company, some satisfied, some self-satisfied and some dissatisfied, each in his own
               mood, passed over to where hung a series of small pictures labeled
                  <title>"City-Life."</title> One of these, a <hi rend="italic">beautiful colored
                  girl</hi>, with a hideous monster of a white-faced doll in her arms, caught the
               "old lady's" eye; and she at once exclaimed, <said>"That is more of your metaphorical
                  nonsense—putting such prejudicial stuff into little children's heads—even before
                  they know they have heads! Set your little boys and girls in the right way of
                  thinking <pb n="246"/><cb/> in the outset: that's what <hi rend="italic">I</hi>
                  say;"</said> and the "old lady" threw herself back into our good old Gallery
               arm-chair, muttering to herself, <said>"what stuff and nonsense these new-fangled
                  colored folks are putting into the heads of our people. They are worse than white
                  folks."</said></p>
            <p>The "tall lady" and the "stout lady" and one of the "white cravats" were quite
               indignant, that such a picture was allowed a place on the walls of the Afric-American
               Picture Gallery. <said>"It is a life-picture,"</said> provokingly chimed in the
               "Philosopher," forgetting his former risk. </p>
            <p><said>"It is an insult to the children,"</said> sarcastically exclaimed the "tall
               lady." <said>"It is an insult to the children,"</said> screached out the "stout
               lady." <said>"It is an insult to the children,"</said> blandly bawled out one of the
               "white cravats;" and he buttoned down his coat, and tried to look very dignified
               indeed; and then they all three looked daggers at the gaunt "Philosopher." </p>
            <p>Turning round to the "lady from abroad," the "tall lady," with a leer said,
                  <said>"what would <hi rend="italic">you</hi> have for our children, Madam? Yes,
                  what would you have?"</said> smirked out the "stout lady." </p>
            <p><said>"Just so, what would you have," </said> defferentially cold drawled out the
               "white cravat," and he again buttoned down his coat. The "lady from abroad" with some
               warmth answered: <said>"Educate first of all things, and above all things, your
                  children to have <hi rend="italic">true self-respect</hi>: yes, I repeat
                  it,"</said> said she with an energy that startled her auditors, <said>"<hi
                     rend="italic">true self-respect</hi>, and then, upon this basis, and this
                  alone, place all their future acquisitions. In the matter before us, I leave you
                  to draw your own conclusions."</said>
            </p>
            <p>This fine proposition caused the "skeptic" to rub his hands with glee, while the
               wiley "Philosopher" made a vain attempt to split it by one of his philosophical
               hair-splitters. </p>
            <p>The "Doctor" and one of the "long black coats" by this time had got quite interested
               and rather warm over <title rend="italic">Picture No. 27</title>, the first
               convention, the "Doctor" maintaining with much pith, that the leading minds of that
               time, who did most to advance the cause of Afric-America, were outside of the clergy;
               and pointed out the leading heads in this fine picture in evidence. It was with a
               glow of delight, that—with stick in hand,—moving from the commanding form and strong
               head of <persName ref="#alexander_hamilton">Hamilton</persName> to the calm <cb/>
               brow and ponderous intellect of <persName ref="henry_sipkins">Sipkins</persName>;
               from the keen phiz and business-like air of <persName ref="#james_forten"
                  >Forten</persName> to the massive head and eagle eye of the fiery <persName
                  ref="#hezekiah_grice">Grice</persName>, or the eloquent, yea almost now speaking
               lips of <persName ref="william_hinton">Hinton</persName>, the cool and determined
                  <persName ref="#bird">Bird</persName>, the polished <persName ref="#burr"
                  >Burr</persName>, the vigorous and clear-sighted <persName ref="#john_bowers"
                  >Bowers</persName>, the strong-minded <persName ref="#vanbrackle">Van
                  Brackle</persName>, and the unswerving <persName ref="#george_vashon"
                  >Vashon</persName>—all, all—and discanted upon their excellencies. </p>
            <p>The "long black coat," cool, cautious, wily and earnest, with equal pertinacity
               pointed out the talented clergy, who led on the host of that day. He pointed to the
               far-seeing <persName ref="#bishop_allen">Bishop Allen</persName>, the able <persName
                  ref="#watkins">Watkins</persName>, the eloquent <persName ref="#corr"
                  >Corr</persName>, the learned and talented <persName ref="#cornish"
                  >Cornish</persName>, the far-seeing <persName ref="#easton">Easton</persName> and
               the faithful <persName ref="#rush">Rush</persName>; all of whom stood to their posts
               in the dark hour of our trial.</p>
            <p>Turning from these, he pointed to the mild and gentle face of <persName
                  ref="#peter_williams">Peter Williams</persName>, who so long led an intelligent
               people on ward and upward to a higher state. This called up reminiscences of the past
               to the "Doctor's" mind; and if it did not convince, it certainly touched him, and he
               was silent. The "wily long black coat" then turned to the portrait of the lamented
                  <persName ref="#theodore_wright">Theodore S. Wright</persName>, and set forth in
               strong light his vast labors and their results. He also pointed out others, who were
               prominent in that clay, and finally exclaimed: <said>"The good they have done, no man
                  can estimate I!! Its influence will vibrate through time, and will continue up
                  into eternity. There hang their portraits,"</said> said he, and he pointed round
               the gallery. <said>Let no man take them down. Let no ruthless hand disturb them ; no
                  polluted finger dare to touch them!! ! There they hang, and there may they hang
                  forever! ! !"</said>
            </p>
            <p>This little patriotic conclusion elicited from the whole company, the "Doctor"
               included, a round of hearty applause. </p>
            <p><said>"There is no metaphorical nonsense about that!"</said> exclaimed the "old
               lady;" and she rose, put up her specs, gathered up the folds of her dress, and walked
               dignifiedly out. </p>
            <p><said>"No metaphorical nonsense about that,"</said> echoed the other of the "white
               cravats," as the " old lady's" last foot-fall sounded down the gallery, and he felt
               again for his dignity, and buttoned down his coat. </p>
            <p>The "Philosopher" pulled out his watch, and began to measure time. The "Doctor," <pb
                  n="247"/><cb/> suddenly jumping up out of a deep brown study, started for the
               door; and the "skeptic" took a stroll down the gallery. The "tall lady" turning up
               what nose she had, and the "stout lady" endeavoring to turn tip what nose she had
               not, at the possibility of "colored folks" ever being improved, at least by their own
               efforts, they both indignantly strode out of the gallery, shaking the very dust off
               the soles of their feet.—</p>
            <p>The "lady from abroad" proceeded to examine some pieces of statuary at the <cb/>upper
               end of the gallery, and made some just criticisms; thereon, while the "little lady in
               black," self-satisfied and prime, sat a model of patience. The "white cravats" and
               "long black coats" adjusted their neckties, buttoned their coats down before, put on
               their hats, drew on their gloves (black ones of course), and quietly departed, wiser
               I trust for their visit; while I, unable to draw any thing but this imperfect sketch,
               hurriedly sent Tom off with it to the <title rend="italic">Anglo African
                  Magazine</title>. </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">(To be Continued.)</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <pb n="321"/>
            <dateline>OCT 1859</dateline>
            <head>Afric-American Picture Gallery. SEVENTH PAPER.</head>
            <byline>BY ETHI0P.</byline>
            <head>The Early Days of the Underground Railroad.</head>
            <cb/>
            <p><persName ref="#bill">Bill</persName> came in one day in a towering rage. It was in
               the earlier days of the Afric American Picture Gallery, when its quiet was seldom
               disturbed by visitors of any kind. </p>
            <p>I started from my old arm-chair in much alarm, and somewhat hastily inquired what the
               matter was. </p>
            <p>Bill's eyes (and I watched him closely) had all the seeming of a fiery demon. His
               large athletic frame seemed to expand with his increased emotion. His broad breast
               heaved to-and-fro like the surges of the ocean lashed with the fury of a storm; while
               his clenched fist continued its hold on a double-barrelled pistol (Colt's revolvers
               where not then in fashion) which lay hid in, his left breast-pocket. </p>
            <p>His countenance, hitherto of dark hue, was now pale, even to ashiness; and his teeth
               gnashed like one of the furies just let loose from the bottomless pit. </p>
            <p><said>"What is the matter,"</said> said I, with increased alarm, <said>"for heaven's
                  sake, say what is the matter?"</said>
            </p>
            <p><said><hi rend="italic">"I have seen him!"</hi></said> said he, with an emphasis that
               made me shudder all over. <said>"I have seen him!"</said> exclaimed he again, still
               more emphatically, <said>"and should he cross my path again, by the" ---------</said>
               The balance of this terrible utterance, happily, was lost on my ear; and without
               abating anything either in appearance or manner, and without another word, he rapidly
               strode the floor, leaving me to supply with my 1 imagination what I could not
               ascertain by inquiry. </p>
            <cb/>
            <p><persName ref="#bill">Bill</persName> was a product of that famous plateau bounded by
                  <placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName>, <placeName>Delaware</placeName>, the
               Atlantic, <placeName>North Carolina</placeName>, and the Alleghany Mountains; and
               which gives out to the country and the world men. </p>
            <p>He was a large, strapping young fellow, just twenty-five, with the proportions of an
               ox, his chest alone having the breadth of two ordinary men. His head was large, his
               face round, his mouth wide, as were his nostrils, and his forehead broad. A real bull
               of Bashan; and yet the general aspect of his countenance was mild, and even pleasant,
               when not under excitement. </p>
            <p>He had formerly been one of a large plantation of ill-used, badly-fed, overworked,
               and ignorant slaves. I say ignorant, because they knew nothing of the world beyond
               their plantation home, and <persName ref="#bill">Bill</persName>, at the time we now
               speak of, had never seen beyond his native hills. But he had a pair of quick eyes,
               two open ears, two strong legs, and a will of his own. </p>
            <p>These, young as he was at that time, he determined to use for his own benefit; and if
               denied him where he was, to seek out some other spot where he could exercise this
               most natural intention.</p>
            <p>How small a circumstance sometimes will turn the point, the vital point in a man's
               destiny, and so it was with our hero.</p>
            <p>White young Northern adventurers, in those days, were in the habit of finding their
               way, summers, down South, seeking employments which paid better than in their own
               sterile New England, or among <pb n="322"/>the cold blue hills of Northern New York. </p>
            <p>One of these fellows, a carpenter, who found his way to the plantation on which Bill
               belonged, now and then, to the slave boys who chanced to be about him, would make
               occasional remarks about the North and New England, and especially his own native
               state, <placeName>Maine</placeName>. <persName ref="#bill">Bill</persName>, dull and
               indifferent, seemed always in the way. His seeming indifference to anything said in
               his hearing by the white help about the plantation gave him excellent advantages, and
               well did he improve them; for he kept up a most wonderful thinking and a strict
               reckoning, and in due time was fully prepared to step out and ascertain for himself
               if all the long yarns and handsome stories he had heard and overheard about the North
               were really true. Why should he not, like other boys, gratify a natural curiosity,
               even if he was only Bill and lived on a plantation; and though, too, it was said that
               he belonged to it ? This latter saying, just here, we may remark, he never could,
               some how or other, fully make up his mind to believe; he never could lead his mind
               fully to believe that he belonged to the plantation or the master thereof. Reasoning
               thus, one Sunday morning, having made previously all due preparation, he obtained
               permission to go a distance in a southward direction, but like a naughty boy turned
               his face northward, not, however, till he had turned himself into a bale of tobacco,
               and took passage in the underground railroad. The road, then, not as now, had but one
               track, and it would have been a novel sight, methinks, to have seen this tobacco,
               alias our Bill, traveling, wheelbarrow fashion, upon the primitive underground
               railroad. </p>
            <p>But such sights are, as a general thing, denied to mortal eyes, and our hero
               proceeded under the strict privacy of a gentle man incog; and arrived in due time
               North, and like a self-unwrapping mummy laid his tobacco, one night, quietly down
               upon the steps of a New England factory, and stepped forth to see the country. </p>
            <p>Thus he got North; and staid North, till early one bright November morning he was
               suddenly roused from his slumbers by a heavy hand; and on rubbing out his eyes and
               looking up who should stand before him but his young master and a posse of officers. </p>
            <p>The place where he was so unceremoni-<cb/>ously woke up was in a humble but
               respectable lodging in <placeName>Calais, Maine</placeName>; the very place he bad so
               often heard of in scraps of story and snatches of song, by the young white employee
               on the old plantation, and had pictured to himself in his dreams of liberty. </p>
            <p>Alas, poor fellow! little did he think that a betrayer almost invariably lurks under
               a white skin; and that the same who seemed more civil than the ferocious Southerner,
               would be the one to send him back to his chains and to the prison-house of bondage
               for a little more than a mess of pottage.</p>
            <p>Jakes, the carpenter, in his wanderings returned to <placeName>Calais</placeName>,
               his native town, and one day discovering <persName ref="#bill">Bill</persName>,
               conceived the idea of replenishing his nearly empty purse by the betrayal of a poor
               fugitive youth, in which he out-Judased Judas Iscariot; for he (Judas) covenanted for
               thirty pieces of silver, while Jakes got only twenty-five. </p>
            <p>Poor modern Judas! Just as the last of his twenty-five pieces was expended, he blew
               out his own brains with a horse-pistol, and his body falling into a stream it swiftly
               drifted out to sea and was made food for the fishes. </p>
            <p><said>"Come, <persName ref="#bill">Bill</persName>! don't you know me? What are you
                  doing here ? Get up you rascal, instantly, and come along! Get up, I tell you, or
                  by"</said> ---</p>
            <p><said>"Massa,"</said> said Bill, <said>"I is so glad you come! for I is so sick and
                  tired of this ere place."</said>
            </p>
            <p>
               <said>"I is been most starved since I run'd away, and is been most naked, too.
                  'Tain't no use to try to get along without Marsar."</said>
            </p>
            <p>So saying he made ready and proceeded with all possible haste with his young master
               to a place of safety. </p>
            <p>However unsound our hero's admissions and reasonings may have seemed to his real
               friends, they were perfectly philosophic to him, and so insured the confidence of his
               master that he dismissed his Northern menials, save one, who acted as a sort of
               lacquey, and forthwith repaired to the South with his man.</p>
            <p><said>"Such complete disgust of this negro of the North will have a most salutary
                  effect upon the rest of the negroes,"</said> said he. <said>"He will be most
                  valuable to the plantations round generally."</said> Thus reasoned the master, as
               he sat the first morning after <pb n="323"/>his arrival home, in his dining room,
               after perusing the morning paper. </p>
            <p>Whoever will take the trouble to examine so far back as our story dates, will find
               this paragraph going the rounds of the <placeName>Calais</placeName>,
                  <placeName>Portland</placeName>, and other <placeName>New England</placeName> and
               many other Northern journals of that day: </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">"The beauties of Negro freedom."</hi>
            </p>
            <p>"A negro, the property of <persName ref="#jd_esq">J. D., Esq.</persName>, of
                  <placeName>Maryland</placeName>, who had, either through the machination of some
               of the enemies to humanity, or his own thick-pated folly, strayed away to the
               North—where the rigors of the climate and the pinchings of hunger had well nigh used
               him up.</p>
            <p>His master, happily, however, arrived just in time to take his too-willing slave
               where, ere this, doubtless, he has been restored to his wonted comfort and happiness;
               and can brood at his leisure over the beauties of <hi rend="italic">Northern
                  freedom</hi>, we mean negro freedom.</p>
            <p>When will the negro learn his simple mission, and his pretended or misguided friends
               learn wisdom." </p>
            <p><persName ref="#bill">Bill</persName>'s arrival was hailed as a great triumph by the
               surrounding slave-owners, especially so when they were made acquainted with his
               sentiments of Northern negro freedom, and its horrors generally. </p>
            <p>Never did poor plantations ring out so many doleful changes on the horrors of the
               North, with <persName ref="#bill">Bill</persName>, poor Bill, for a standing example;
               and very soon he was exalted to a kind of exhorter or lay preacher among his colored
               brethren. </p>
            <p>But while the masters were thus teaching over Bill's back the horrors of Northern
               freedom and the North generally, Bill, wide awake, and adroit in manner, was
               instructing far more effectively in quite the opposite direction. </p>
            <p>Such an unusual number of slaves decamped that summer, that a convention of the
               neighboring masters was held to enquire into the cause, and, if possible, provide an
               immediate remedy. </p>
            <p>No one, of course, suspected Bill. His notions of Northern negro freedom, and
               earnestness in the interest of the master, continually and publicly expressed, placed
               him too high in general estimation for that. Still decade after decade of the "Boys"
               foolishly forsook their kind masters for the <cb/> unknown regions of the hated
               North. </p>
            <p>In course of time <persName ref="#bill">Bill</persName> was also again missing. Yes,
               Bill, the faithful, penitent Bill, the negro exhorter. </p>
            <p>Nothing could exceed the consternation, chagrin and rage among the plantation owners
               generally, and Bill's especially, when it became fully established that Bill, the
               least suspected, had, for the second time, betook to his heels for parts to them
               unknown. </p>
            <p>Pursuit, hot pursuit, was the cry that ran along the line of the plantations, and two
               of the most celebrated, wreckless and daring of the negro catchers quickly
               volunteered to overtake and return, dead or alive, this daring and dangerous negro. </p>
            <p>Without a moment's loss of time these fellows set out and pushed forward. </p>
            <p>For a correct account of what followed from this point of our story we must extract
               from Bill's own narrative of the affair. He says, <said>"Time and experience had
                  taught me many things, and I was this time fully prepared for any and every
                  emergency. I started under cover of a stormy winter's night and proceeded many
                  miles ere the sun of another day broke the darkness. I then refreshed and rested
                  myself in a well-retired place, resuming my journey soon after the next
                  night-fall. After some three hours' travel, came to a cross-bridge overhung by
                  large beechen trees, with thick underbrush lining the sides of the deep chasm
                  beneath.</said></p>
            <p>
               <said>"Just as I had got about midway of this bridge, I descried through the thick
                  darkness two men stealthily approaching from an opposite direction, and so close
                  upon me that retreat was useless.</said>
            </p>
            <p>
               <said>"'Stand!' demanded the well-known voice of a most dreaded negro catcher, and
                  quickly made for me, while I, with the rapidity of lightning almost, leveled my
                  pistol at the other and remoter man, who in an instant rolled heavily over on the
                  bridge without a groan.</said>
            </p>
            <p>
               <said>"The first was now so near that there was nothing left for either of us but to
                  close in the deadly hand-to-hand struggle He, though a powerful man and used to
                  conflict, finding his inability to overpower me, endeavored to draw his pistol on
                  me, which I, either by tact or superiority of strength, averted, and it harmlessly
                  exploded in the air. </said>
            </p>
            <p>
               <said>"It was now my turn. Liberty or death <pb n="324"/><cb/> with me, and life or
                  death with him. The struggle was a fearful one. It was up, it was down; it was
                  down, it was up.</said>
            </p>
            <p>
               <said>"Not a word was spoken; not a murmur, not a whisper escaped either of us. He
                  got me round the waist, I him by the throat. It was dark; but yet through that
                  darkness so livid and changed became his countenance, and so glaring his eyes (I
                  can see him even now), that, though knowing him well, it seemed it was the very
                  devil with which I was dealing.</said>
            </p>
            <p>"<said>But I held my grasp, increasing it only in tightness. I neither could, nor
                  cared, to do otherwise.</said>
            </p>
            <p>"<said>There seemed to be a charm upon me as I gazed into his livid face; a spell
                  that worked upon my fingers as I held him.</said>
            </p>
            <p>
               <said>"His limbs, which, for a moment, assumed the rigidity of iron, suddenly
                  relaxed; his eyes, like an exploded lamp, suddenly flared out; his vice-like arms
                  which bound me fell down. A strange emotion came over me. I knew nothing but one
                  convulsive effort.</said>
            </p>
            <p>
               <said>"I then listened: I heard a loud splash some thirty or forty feet below, which
                  told me all I wished to know.</said>
            </p>
            <p>
               <said>"Seized with the same spirit, I ran to the other lifeless carcase and gave it
                  one heave, and with another splash it followed its mate to where no tales are
                  told, and <cb/>where earthly quiet reigns supreme." </said>
            </p>
            <p><said>"I had decided the question of my own liberty,"</said> says he, <said>"this
                  time, before I left the plantation; and because God had im planted the principles
                  of liberty in my bosom, both in seeking and maintaining that liberty, I had
                  determined to remove every obstacle that obtruded itself between me and
               it.</said></p>
            <p>
               <said>"I did, therefore, nothing more than my duty to myself, to my manhood, and to
                  my God."</said>
            </p>
            <p><said>"After the incident of the bridge which I have narrated,"</said> says he,
                  <said> "no further impediments came in my way, and I soon found myself North,
                  where I had determined, come what would, to take up my abode."</said>
            </p>
            <p>It was on the morning on which our story commences, when <persName ref="#bill"
                  >Bill</persName> entered our Gallery under the excitement we have described, and
               exclaiming, <said><hi rend="italic">"I have seen him, have seen him!"</hi></said>
               that the man who claimed to be his owner passed him in the street, and fortunate for
               that man that he did not see <persName ref="#bill">Bill</persName>; fortunate for the
               community that they passed and did not meet. </p>
            <p>The portrait of our sable hero, in all the flush of manhood, hangs on the north side
               of the Gallery, for the inspection of the curious.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
