<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="ecda.odd%20copy.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:ecda="http://dsg.northeastern.edu/ecda/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Theresa: A Haytien Tale</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
     <ecda:hyperDiv>
        <ecda:notes>
           <note type="ecda" xml:id="ana_interp">
              <interpGrp>
                 <interp xml:id="food">references to items (either food or drink) that could be consumed</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="flora">references to plants (e.g. trees, flowers, etc.)</interp>
                 <interp xml:id="fauna">references to animals (e.g. birds, insects, etc.)</interp>
              </interpGrp>
              <interpGrp>
                 <interp xml:id="punishment">references to items/actions used to punish people and/or instances of 
                    punishment
                 </interp>
                 <interp xml:id="military">references to materials, persons, and events specifically related to
                    military action
                 </interp>
              </interpGrp>
           </note>
           <note type="ecda">
              <!-- Some notes on encoding practices for this document -->
              <p>The encoding methodology for this document is based off of the encoding practices for the Early
                  Caribbean Digital Archive. While this document reflects some established markup policies, the 
                  ODD file for this project is still being customized.
              </p>
              <p>At present, the ECDA transcribes and encodes document from reproductions of the original text.
                 This text, however, is a transcription. Therefore this encoded document does not follow ECDA 
                 practices surrounding reproduction of rendition, preservation of page breaks, and 
                 correction/regularization policies.
              </p>
              <list>
                 <head>At the time of this document's creation, the ECDA recorded the presence of the following:</head>
                 <item>Personal names using <gi>persName</gi>.</item>
                 <item>Names of places using <gi>placeName</gi>.</item>
                 <item>Names of geographical landmarks using <gi>geogName</gi>.</item>
                 <item>Names of groups of people using <gi>name</gi>.</item>
                 <item>References to anonymous persons using <gi>ecda:anonPers</gi>.</item>
                 <item>References to commodities using <gi>ecda:commodity</gi>.</item>
                 <item>References to plants/animals/food using <gi>ecda:flora</gi>, <gi>ecda:fauna</gi>,
                    and <gi>ecda:food</gi>.
                 </item>
                 <item><gi>rs</gi> is used to record references to persons/places/groups that are not explicitly 
                    named. These receive values on <att>type</att> of:
                    <list>
                       <item><val>person</val></item>
                       <item><val>place</val></item>
                       <item><val>persGroup</val></item>
                       <item><val>properAdjective</val></item>
                    </list>
                    The <gi>rs</gi> element in this document is only used once per paragraph for each individual
                    reference to a person/place. So, if a person is referenced by name, and then by title later in
                    the paragraph, <gi>rs</gi> is not used. If a person is referenced by title or role three times 
                    in a paragraph, but never by name, <gi>rs</gi> is used only in the <emph>first</emph> instance,
                    and all other references remain unencoded
                 </item>
                 <item>The ECDA also encodes basic structural elements such as:
                    <list>
                       <item><gi>front</gi></item>
                       <item><gi>body</gi></item>
                       <item><gi>back</gi></item>
                       <item><gi>div</gi>, where <gi>div</gi> is assigned a value for <att>type</att></item>
                       <item><gi>p</gi></item>
                       <item><gi>floatingText</gi></item>
                    </list>
                 </item>
              </list>
              <p>The ECDA is currently working on a large-scale contextual encoding project, which will allow
                 for entries on people (both anonymous and named), places, bibliographic items, organizations,
                 etc. A miniature, document-specific version of the ECDA's contextual encoding can be seen in
                 the personography (<seg corresp="#personography">see the "personographical note"</seg>). For 
                 this document, only references to persons are linked to a personography, and place/group
                 -ographies are not recorded.
              </p>
              <p>In an attempt to track references to commodities, the ECDA has come up with a policy for encoding
                 the presence of objects, both commodified and not, in texts. For this we use <seg><att>ana</att>
                 and <gi>interp</gi>.</seg> Since many of the things we are tracking are either plants or animals,
                 we added <gi>ecda:flora</gi> and <gi>ecda:fauna</gi> elements. <att>ana</att> can be applied to
                 either of these elements, along with <gi>ecda:commodity</gi> and <gi>ecda:food</gi>. The <att>ana</att>
                 attribute allows the ECDA to encode multiple descriptors of objects simultaneously, allowing for
                 a larger number of possibilities for the markup. This document also contains <val>punishment</val>
                 and <val>military</val> as values on <att>ana</att> to record the presence of these concepts within
                 the document. Descriptions of all of the values for <att>ana</att> can be found in the 
                 <seg corresp="#ana_interp">analysis and interpretation note.</seg>
              </p>
           </note>
           <note type="personographical" xml:id="personography">
              <listPerson>
                 <person xml:id="theresa">
                    <persName>
                       <forename>Theresa</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <residence>
                       Resident of
                       <placeName>Haiti</placeName>
                    </residence>
                    <sex>female</sex>
                 </person>
                 <person xml:id="amanda">
                    <persName>
                       <forename>Amanda</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <residence>
                       Resident of
                       <placeName>Haiti</placeName>
                    </residence>
                    <sex>female</sex>
                 </person>
                 <person xml:id="paulina">
                    <persName>
                       <forename>Paulina</forename>
                    </persName>
                    <residence>
                       Resident of
                       <placeName>Haiti</placeName>
                    </residence>
                    <sex>female</sex>
                 </person>
                 <person xml:id="anon_brother">
                    <ecda:anonPers/>
                    <occupation>revolutionist leader</occupation>
                    <residence>resident of
                       <placeName>Haiti</placeName>
                    </residence>
                    <sex>male</sex>
                 </person>
                 <person xml:id="anon_lieutenant">
                    <occupation>lieutenant</occupation>
                    <sex>male</sex>
                 </person>
                 <person xml:id="louverture_1743">
                    <persName>
                       <forename>Toussaint</forename>
                       <surname>L'Ouverture</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <birth when="1743-05-20"/>
                    <death when="1803-04-07"/>
                    <occupation>general</occupation>
                    <residence>resident of
                       <placeName>Haiti</placeName>
                    </residence>
                    <faith>Roman Catholic</faith>
                    <sex>male</sex>
                 </person>
                 <person xml:id="inginac_0001">
                    <persName>
                       <forename>Joseph</forename>
                       <forename>Balthasar</forename>
                       <surname>Inginac</surname>
                    </persName>
                    <occupation>general</occupation>
                    <residence>resident of
                       <placeName>Haiti</placeName>
                    </residence>
                    <sex>male</sex>
                 </person>
                 <relation type="familial" name="mother-daughter" mutual="#paulina #theresa"/>
                 <relation type="familial" name="mother-daughter" mutual="#paulina #amanda"/>
                 <relation type="familial" name="sister" mutual="#amanda #theresa"/>
              </listPerson>
           </note>
        </ecda:notes>
     </ecda:hyperDiv>
      <body>
         <div type="entry">
            <head>For the Freedom's Journal.</head>
            <head type="main">Theresa,</head>
            <head type="sub">A <rs type="properAdjective">Haytien</rs> Tale</head>
            <p>During the long and bloody contest, in <placeName>St. Domingo</placeName> between the <rs type="persGroup">white 
               man</rs>, who flourished at the child of sensuality, rioting on the miseries of his slaves; had the 
               <rs type="persGroup">sons of Africa</rs>, who, provoked to madness and armed themselves against 
               <rs type="properAdjective">French</rs> barbarity; <persName ref="#paulina">Madame Paulina</persName> was left a widow, unhappy
               —unprotected, and exposed to all the horrors of the revolution. Not without much unhappiness, she saw that if 
               she would save her life from the inhumanity of <rs type="persGroup"><rs type="place">her country</rs>'s enemy</rs>, 
               she must depart from the endeared village of her innocent childhood; still dear to her, though now it was become 
               a theatre of many tragic scenes. The once verdant plains, round its environs had been crimsoned with the blood of 
               innocence, and the nature of the times afforded no security to the <rs type="persGroup">oppressed natives</rs> of 
               <placeName>Saint Nicholas</placeName>.
            </p>
            <p>Famine which had usurped the place of plenty and happiness, with her associate security, were banished from the 
               humble dwellings of the injured <name>Haytiens</name>.
            </p>
            <p>After much unpleasant reflections on her pitiable situation <persName ref="#paulina">Madame Paulina</persName> resolved to 
               address a letter, soliciting the advice of <ecda:anonPers ref="#anon_brother">her brother</ecda:anonPers>, then at <placeName>Cape 
               Marie'</placeName>, and a the head of a party of his patriot brethren, who like him, disdained slavery, and were
               determined to live free men, or expire in their attempts for liberty and independence. But reason had scarce 
               approved this suggestion of her mind, when suddenly she heard a simultaneous <seg ana="#military">volley of musketry</seg>, and the 
               appalling roaring of <seg ana="#military">heavy artillery</seg> rumbling along the mountain's ridge, like terrifying thunders; to this 
               distant warfare, the lapse of fifteen minutes brought a cessation, which announced, that on either side, many 
               that were, had ceased to be. Silence having ensued, there was a stillness in the air. All at <placeName>Saint 
               Nicholas</placeName>, desirous to know the issue of the combat, remained in doubtful anxiety.
            </p>
            <p>Each one's heart was the abode of fear and doubt, while the dense smoke, escaping the despot's fury, and 
               evading the implacable resentment of <rs type="persGroup">those armed in the justice of their cause</rs>, was 
               seen to overtop the dusky hills, winding its way upwards in sulphureous columns, as if, to supplicate at the 
               Eternal's Throne, and plead the cause of the injured.
            </p>
            <p>The <name>French</name> in this combat with the <name>Revolutionists</name>, suffered much, both from the 
               extreme sultriness of the day, and the courage of those with whom they contended; disappointed and harassed by 
               the <name>Islanders</name>; they thought it a principle of policy, to <seg ana="#punishment">resort to acts of cruelty</seg>; and to 
               intimidate them, resolved, that none of them should be spared; but that the sword should annihilate, or compel 
               them to submit to their wonted degradations; and <placeName>St. Nicholas</placeName> was the unfortunate 
               village, first to be devoted to the resentful rage of the cruel enemy. All the natives were doomed to suffer; 
               the mother and the infant that reposed on her bosom, fell by the same sword, while groans of the sick served 
               only as the guides which disovered them to the inhumanity of the inexorable, at whose hands they met a miserable
               death.
            </p>
            <p>The sun was fast receding to the west, as if ashamed of man's transactions, boasting itself in the dark mantle 
               of twilight, when <persName>Gen. Le' <!-- unsure what this means --></persName>, <seg ana="#military #punishment">fired the few dwellings,</seg> then 
               remaining in the village. Misery was now <sic>grabbed</sic> <!-- corr garbed? --> in her most terrifying robes,
               and terror possessed itself the heart of all, except the <name>French</name>, in whose hands were placed the 
               <seg ana="#military #punishment">weapons of destruction</seg>.
            </p>
            <p>The intelligence of the defeat of the army recently stationed at <placeName>Cape Marie</placeName>, reached the
               ears of the unhappy <persName ref="#paulina">Paulina</persName>, and with horror she heard that her beloved brother in his 
               attempt to regain <placeName>St. Nicholas</placeName>, breathed out his valuable life in the cause of freedom, 
               and for <rs type="place">his country</rs>. But it was now no time to indulge in grief—Safety was the object of 
               the <rs type="persGroup">wretched villagers</rs>.
            </p>
            <p>To effect an escape from the horrors of this ominous night, was difficult in the extreme; for the passes leading 
               out into the country were all occupied by the <seg ana="#military">enemy's troops</seg>, whe were not only vigilant, but relentless and 
               cruel. <persName ref="#paulina">Madame Paulina</persName> apprehended her own danger, but her greatest solicitude was for the 
               safety of <rs type="person" ref="#theresa #amanda">her daughters</rs>, who in the morning of life, were expanding like the foliages of the rose into elegance 
               and beauty. She had kept them long concealed from the knowledge of the enemy, whose will she knew was their law, 
               and whose law was injustice—the mother's wretchedness, and the daughter's shame and ruin. In happier days, when 
               peace plessed her native island, she had seen a small hut, during a summer's excursion, in an unfrequented sot, 
               in the delightful valley of <geogName>Vega Real</geogName>, and on the eastern bank of the beautiful
               <geogName>Yuma</geogName>; and now she resolved if possible, to retreat thither with both her daughters.
            </p>
            <p>Necessity being the source of human inventions, was now ready to commune with her mind on subjects of moment, 
               and to give birth to the events of its decision—and in the midst of the general uproar which the village now 
               was—The shrieks of the defenceless, the horrible clashing of arms, and the expiring groans of the aged,
               <persName ref="#paulina">Paulina</persName> hurried herself in the execution of her plans for escaping.
            </p>
            <p>With a <seg>feigned passport and letter</seg>, she ingeniously contrived to pass out of the village conducting her 
               daughters, like the pious <persName type="allusion">Aeneas</persName>, through all the horrors, in which 
               <placeName>St. Nicholas</placeName> was now involved.
            </p>
            <p>But though protected by the mantle of night Madame was hastening on her way to safety and quiet; she frequently 
               would turn her eyes bathed with the dew of sorrow, and heave her farewell sigh towards her ill-fated village; 
               and like <!-- is this an unclear/gap mark? --> when departing out of <placeName>Sodom</placeName>,
               <persName ref="#paulina">Paulina</persName> prayed for mercy for the enemies of her country, and the destroyers of her peace. 
               She and <rs type="person" ref="#amanda #theresa">her daughters</rs>, driven by cruel ambition, from their peaceful abodes were wretched. Their souls were 
               occupied by fearful doubts and anxiety. Every whisper of the winds among the leaves of the 
               <ecda:flora ana="#food">plantain</ecda:flora> and <ecda:flora ana="#food">orange trees</ecda:flora>, caused her 
               daughters to apprehend the approach of danger, and she to heave the anxious sigh.
            </p>
            <p>The <ecda:fauna>green lizard</ecda:fauna> crossed not the road in the way to its hole, at the noise of the
               fugitives feet, but they beheld through the shade of the night a body of the enemy; the distant glare of the 
               firefly, was a light which pointed to the enemies camps; while the <ecda:fauna>bat</ecda:fauna> beating the 
               <!-- ditto prev comment --> in its nocturnal ranges, often was the false messenger of danger to the fair 
               adventurers. Every tree kissed by zephyrs, that ruffled its leaves, was an army approaching, and in the trunk of
               every decored <ecda:flora>mahogany</ecda:flora>, was seen a <name>Frenchman</name> in ambush— not less alarming 
               to the fugitives, were the ripe fruit that frequently fell to the earth. Then having turned to a by-path, 
               <persName ref="#paulina">Paulina</persName> felt herself more secure; and with a soul oppressed with mingled grief and joy, she 
               with maternal affection embraced <rs type="person" ref="#theresa #amanda">her daughters</rs>, and observed to them, that however 
               just may be the cause which induces us to practice duplicity, or the laudable object which gives birth to
               hypocrisy. Truth alone can make us happy, and prevent the Internal Judge of the human mind, filling us with 
               fearful apprehensions, and painting to our imaginations the result which would attend detection. <seg>S.</seg>
            </p>
            <trailer>(To be Continued.)</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <head>Theresa</head>
            <head type="sub">A <rs type="properAdjective">Haytien</rs> Tale</head>
            <p>Morning had just began to peep forth, and the golden rays of the returning sun were seen to burnish the tops 
               of the <seg>majestic cibiao mountians</seg>, when the bewildered adventurers were suddenly startled by the 
               <seg ana="#military">shrill blast of a bugle</seg>; their surprise was not less than their wretchedness, when at no great distance, they 
               beheld approaching them <seg ana="#military">a detachment of the enemies cavalry</seg>. At this unexpected crisis <persName ref="#paulina">madame 
               Paulina</persName> overcome with fearful apprehensions, trembled lest she should be wanting in the discharge 
               of her difficult undertaking. But it was now too late; she must either act well her part or be reconducted by 
               <rs type="persGroup">the foe</rs> <!-- ? Nicholas -->, and there, after witnessing the destruction of those
               for whose happiness, she was more concerned, than her own, <seg ana="#punishment">receive a cruel and ingominous death</seg>.
            </p>
            <p>The party of horsemen being now very near, she gave some necessary instructions to her daughters, and conducted
               them onward with no little confidence in her success. The <ecda:anonPers ref="#anon_lieutenant" ana="#military">lieutenant,</ecda:anonPers> by whom
               the <name>French</name> were commanded, observing her attired in the <seg ana="#military #sartorial">uniform of a <rs type="properAdjective">French</rs> 
               officer</seg>, took her for what she so well affected to be—(a captain of the <rs type="properAdjective">French</rs> 
               army) he made to her the order of the day, and enquired the time she left <placeName>St, Nicholas</placeName>, and 
               whether conducting the two prisoners, (for <persName ref="#paulina">Paulina</persName> had the presence of mind to disguise her
               daughters as such) she replied, and taking forth her letter, she handed it to the lieutenant. Succeeding thus far 
               admirably, our adventuress was led to make some enquiries relative to the welfare of the 
               <rs type="properAdjective">French</rs> troops, stationed west of <placeName>St. Nicholas</placeName>, and having 
               collected much valuable information, they parted, and <persName ref="#paulina">Madame Paulina</persName> favoured by a ready 
               address, and with much fortitude escaped death—conducting the dear objects of her tender solicitude far, from the
               ill-fated village of their infancy.
            </p>
            <p>Being informed by the <ecda:anonPers ref="anon_lieutenant" ana="#military">lieutenant</ecda:anonPers>, that at the distance of a view miles, there were encamped a company of the 
               <name>French</name>, she thought it judicious to avoid all public roads, and having turned into a think grove of 
               the <ecda:flora>Pimento trees</ecda:flora>, she proposed to her daughters to rest in this spot until darkness again
               should unfold her mantle.
            </p>
            <p>In this grove of quiet security, the troubled souls of the fugitives ceased partially to be oppressed with fear—the 
               milky juice of the <ecda:food ana="#flora">cocoanut</ecda:food> allayed their thirst and moistened their parched
               lips, and the delicious <ecda:food ana="#flora">orange</ecda:food>, and the luxurious <ecda:food ana="flora">mango</ecda:food>,
               in spontaneous abundance, yielded a support to their nearly exhausted natures.
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="#paulina">Madame Paulina</persName> and her daughters were now seated under the shade of a majestic spreading 
               <ecda:flora ana="#food">Guava</ecda:flora>. The day was fast declining, and though the heat of <name>July</name>
               was intensely oppresive; in this secluded spot, the air was rendered freagrant with the variety of
               <sic>arometic</sic> shrubs, that grew spontaneously in this grove of peace. The <ecda:fauna>hummingbird</ecda:fauna>
               skipping capriciously from blossom to blossom, displayed its magnificent plumange, and for a while diverted the 
               minds of <rs type="persGroup" ref="#paulina #amanda #theresa">the unhappy fugitives</rs> from grief and ominous forbodings; wearied and fatigued
               by a journey which was not less tiresome than hazardous, their much exhausted natures, were greatly refreshed by 
               the cool breeze which gave to their whole bodies a calm sensation, in which their souls soon participated and 
               Madame and her eldest daughter were now lost in the arms of sleep, 
               the kind restorer of vigour to the minds and bodies of men. All around was now still, save the 
               <ecda:fauna>western woodpecker</ecda:fauna> was heard at times to peck the hollow trunk of some decayed tree, or 
               the distant roaring of heavy cannon, which announced that all creative beings were born to enjoy peace, but man, who
               stimulated by ambition, is more cruel than the beasts of the forest, which soil he ever renders fertile with the 
               blood of his victims. But <persName ref="#theresa">Mademoiselle Theresa</persName>, the youngest of the three adventurers, greeted 
               not sleep. The vigour of her body was indeed much exhausted, but the emotions of her mind were more active than ever;
               she saw with the mind's eye the great services which might be rendered to her country; she brought to her
               imagination the once delightful fields of her native <placeName>Hayti</placeName>, now dy'd with the blood of her 
               countrymen in their righteous struggle for liberty and for independence.
            </p>
            <p>Not less did she contemplate the once flourishing plantations ruined and <!-- ?? Domingo --> once the 
               <!-- grana yo --> the <placeName>West Indies</placeName> reduced to famine, now the island of misery, and the abode 
               of wretchedness.
            </p>
            <p>It was but the last night, that she witnessed the most terrifying scenes of her life—when the shrieks of her dying 
               friends made her apprehend justly what her own fate must be, should she fail to effect an excape from the village 
               of her happiest days. <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName> thought of the brave <persName type="allusion">St. Clair</persName>; she imagined 
               she saw <rs type="person">her beloved uncle</rs> <seg ana="#punishment">weltering in his blood, and the barbarous <name>French</name> 
               fixing his venerable head on a pole</seg>, and it exposed on a cross road, as the head of a rebel. She shuddered at this 
               thought; her soul was subdued, and the fount of grief issued from her eyes in copious streams, bathing her febrile 
               cheeks with dews of sorrow. <said rend="quotes">Why,</said> said she, <said rend="quotes">O, my God! hast thou 
               suffered thy creatures to be thus afflicted in all thy spacious earth? Are we too thy children? And didst thou not 
               cover us with this sable exterior, by which our race is distinguished, and for which they are contemned and ever 
               been cruelly persecuted! O, my God—my God!—be propitious to the cause of justice—be near to the <name>Haytiens</name> 
               in their righteous struggle, to obtain those rights which thou has graciously bestowed on all thy children. Raise up 
               some few of those, who have been long degraded—give to them dominion, and enable them to govern a state of their 
               own—so that the proud and cruel may know that thou art alike the Father of the native of the burning desert, and of 
               the more temperate region.</said>
            </p>
            <trailer>(To be concluded in our next.)</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="entry">
            <head>Theresa</head>
            <head type="sub">A <rs type="properAdjective">Haytien</rs> Tale (Continued.)</head>
            <p>It was in the presence of <persName ref="theresa">Theresa</persName> that the conversation between <persName>M. L'Motelle</persName> and her heroic 
               mother took place. <persName ref="#paulina">Madame Paulina</persName>, on her part leaving nothing undone, which might serve to 
               accomplish the object for which she had been induced to practice duplicity; <persName>M. L'Motelle</persName> 
               regarded her for what she really appeared to be; and unhesitatingly spoke of matters concerning the nature of the 
               times; of the military and local situations of the <rs type="properAdjective">French</rs> troops; their condition 
               and strength were topics of interest; and <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName> learned that the distance to the camp of 
               the brave <persName ref="#louverture_1743">Touissant, L'Ouverture</persName>, was a single league from the place where he communicated 
               the intelligence. Seeming to be inattentive, she pensively bent her eyes towards the earth, listening the while as 
               he unconsciously developed many military schemes, which were about being executed, and if successful, would, in all 
               probability, terminate in the destruction of the <name>Revolutionists</name>, and, in the final success of the 
               <rs type="properAdjective">French</rs> power in this island. These were invaluable discoveries, and could they be made 
               known in due time to those against whose rights, their injustice was intended, it would not fail to give success to 
               <rs type="properAdjective">Haytien</rs> independence, disappoint the arch-enemy, and aid the cause of humanity. But, 
               alas! important as they were to the cause of freedom, by whom shall they be carried.
            </p>
            <p>Who shall reveal them to the <name><sic>Revoluists</sic></name>. No one interested was near, and they were in the
               possession of none friendly to the cause of justice, except three defenceless ones. <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName> 
               herself must be the bearer, or survive only to witness them executed agreeably to the desires of the enemy. In what 
               manner must she act? The salvation of her oppressed country to her, was an object of no little concern; but she also 
               owed a duty to <rs type="person" ref="#paulina">that mother</rs>, whose tender solicitude for her happiness, could not be surpassed 
               by any parent, and <rs type="person" ref="#amanda">a sister</rs> too, whom she tenderly loved, and whose attachment to her was 
               undivided. Her absence from the grove, she was confidently assured, would be to them their greatest source of 
               affliction; it would probably terminate the already much exhausted life of her dear mother, and complete the measure 
               of <persName ref="#amanda">Amanda's</persName> wretchedness. Her own inexperience in the manner, she should conduct in an affair 
               so important and hazardous, was an obstacle which in connexion with her sense of duty, and care for her mother's 
               happiness, would deter her from embarking in it. She paused, then as if aroused by some internal agent, exclaimed 
               <said>Oh, <placeName>Hayti</placeName>!—be independent, and let <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName> be the unworthy 
               sacrifice offered to that God, who shall raise his mighty arm in defence of thy injured children.</said> She drew 
               from her bosom a pencil and wrote on a piece of bark of the <ecda:flora>Gourd tree</ecda:flora>, telling her mother 
               and <persName ref="#amanda">Amanda</persName>, whither she was gone—her errand; begged that, they would not be unhappy on account 
               of her absence; that they would remain at their place of peace and quiet, until she should return to them with an 
               escort, who should conduct them to a safer retreat, and commit them to the protection of friend. This scroll, 
               <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName> pinned on her mother's coat, while she and <persName ref="#amanda">Amanda</persName> were yet indulging 
               in repose, and like an heroine of the age of chivalry, she forsook the grove of <ecda:flora>Pimento</ecda:flora> and 
               hastened on her way to the camp of <persName ref="#louverture_1743">L'Ouverture</persName>. She had scarce reached the third part of her 
               journey when her mother dreaming, that one of her daughters had been borne off by an officer of the enemy, awoke from 
               sleep and missing <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName>, believed her dream prophetic. It was now that the keenest anguish 
               filled her soul. <persName ref="#paulina">Paulina</persName> wished not to live. Life to a mother thus sorely afflicted, is misery—she
               would go in search of the dear object of all her <sic>affliction</sic>, but where, she knew not. Keen is the grief of 
               a mother, whose child has been forced from her. She is extremely wretched, and her affliction then, cannot be less 
               severe, than it was when in the anguish and sorrow of her soul, the dear object of her tenderest solicitude was 
               introduced into the world, to take its station among the Probationers for eternity. <persName ref="#amanda">Amanda</persName> was 
               now awakened by the unhappy and pitiful grief of her bewildered mother. Hastily she enquired for her sister;
               <persName ref="#paulina">Paulina</persName> in a burst of grief and wild despair, told her, she had been borne off while they slept; 
               with half articulated accents, she related her ominous dream, and the fact was now realized in her absence from the 
               grove. An icy chillness pervaded her whole nature—a dark mist covered her eyes—all the objects by which she was 
               surrounded seemed to recede—her senses were bewildered, and <persName ref="#amanda">Amanda</persName>, unobserved by her mother, 
               swooned and fell to the earth, But soon recovering, she beheld the piece of <ecda:flora>Gourd bark</ecda:flora> pinned 
               to the skirt of her mother's coat—she hastened to un pin—it was the hand writing of <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName>—they 
               read it with avidity—joyful in the happy discovery, the mother and the daughter was perched upon their tongues, while 
               the tears of mingled joy and sorrow poured from their eyes; The troubles of their souls were greatly subsided, but 
               happiness could not be restored, until the success of <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName> be ascertained, and she again be 
               encircled in their arms.
            </p>
            <p>It was uncertain whether she could, in safety reach the camp of the <name>Revolutionists</name>; the roads were at all 
               times travelled by reconnoitering parties of the <name>French</name>; and what could be the fate of the heroic 
               <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName>, if taken by any of them! How cruel would be her usage, particularly, if her intentions 
               and the circumstances, which gave them birth be known. Death inevitable would deprive the world of one so fair, 
               virtuous, and so noble.
            </p>
            <p>Such were the thoughts of <rs type="person" ref="#paulina">the mother</rs> and <rs type="person" ref="#amanda">sister</rs> of the noble adventuress. 
               But while they were thus grieving, <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName>, favoured by fortune, had safely arrived at the 
               military quarters of the great <persName ref="#louverture_1743">Toussant</persName>: had communicated to the chieftain the object of her 
               visit to his camp, and was receiving all the distinctions due her exalted virtue, and which her dauntless resolution 
               so justly merited.
            </p>
            <p>The sun was now fast receding behind the lofty <ecda:flora>Cibao</ecda:flora>, whose rugged summits in the morning,
               appeared burnished by its resplendent rays, and darkness was out-stretching <sic>here</sic> spacious mantle. The 
               <ecda:flora ana="food">orange</ecda:flora> and <ecda:flora ana="#food">citron</ecda:flora> groves, and all the rich 
               enameled luxuriance of torrid luxuries, now began to wear a sombre aspect, while the chattering 
               <ecda:fauna>Paroquet</ecda:fauna> ceased to imitate man, and disturb the sweets of solitude, with prating garrulity, 
               had retired to her roost on the sturdy <ecda:flora>logwood</ecda:flora>. Now it was, that <persName ref="theresa">Theresa</persName>,
               under a strong military escort, left the general's camp of hospitality, retracing her steps towards the grove of 
               <ecda:flora>Pimento</ecda:flora>, where, at her departure, she left her dear mother and <persName ref="#amanda">Amanda</persName>,
               enjoying a calm repose; seated in a close carriage, her thoughts reverted to the deplorable state of her country; with 
               a prophetic eye she saw the destruction of the <name>French</name>, and their final expulsion from her native island. 
               She entreated the Creator, that he would bless the means, which through her agency, he had been pleased to put in the 
               possession of her too long oppressed countrymen, and that all might be made useful to the cause of freedom. But turning
               her thoughts toward her <rs type="person" ref="#paulina">mother</rs> and sister, <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName> was conscious, that her 
               absence from the grove could not fail to have given them extreme sorrow and unhappiness; her gentle nature recoiled at 
               the recollection, and she gave way to a flood of tears. But recollecting again the important services, she had rendered
               her aggrieved country and to the <rs type="properAdjective">Haytien</rs> people—the objects which prompted her to
               disobedience, which induced her to overstep the bounds of modest, and expose to immediate dangers her life and sex. 
               She felt that her conduct was exculpated, and self-reproach was lost in the consciousness of her laudable efforts to 
               save <placeName>St. Domingo</placeName>. Her noble soul re-animated, recovered its wonted calm, as the ocean its quiet 
               motion when the gentle breeze, and the returned sunshine, succeeded a tempestuous sky and boisterous winds.
            </p>
            <p>S.</p>
            <trailer>(To be concluded in our next.)</trailer>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Theresa</head>
            <head type="sub">A <rs type="properAdjective">Haytien</rs> Tale. Concluded.</head>
            <p>Fated to experience trials, she was now to be made more wretched than ever. <!--<persName> or <placeName>St. Lewis</placeName></persName>--> was now 
               near the forward progressing company of his brethren in arms. He had been despatched to the 
               <ecda:flora>Pimento</ecda:flora> grove, to acquaint <persName ref="#paulina">madame Paulina</persName> and <persName ref="#amanda">Amanda</persName>
               of the approach of their dear <persName ref="theresa">Theresa</persName>. But, alas! by whom, or how was the doleful news to be 
               reported to the heroine? Her mother and sister were not to be found at 
               the place where she had left them: and who shall keep the shocking intelligence from her! Already she saw him 
               approaching; he was now near. She observed the gloomy melancholy, which settled on his brow, that plainly foretold 
               all were not well. She inquired into the result of his journey to the grove, and as an earthquake rends the bosom
               of the earth, so the intelligence her gentle soul.
            </p>
            <p><said>Oh! <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName>!—<persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName>!</said>said she in bitter grief, <said>thou art 
               the murderer of a <rs type="person" ref="#paulina">mother</rs> and a loving <rs type="person" ref="#amanda">sister</rs>! Where! where shall I hide
               me from the displeasure of heaven and the curse of man!—Oh, matricide! matricide! whither shalt thou flee from thy 
               accusing conscience! In life I shall be wretched, and after death, oh! who shall release this soul from the bonds of 
               self-condemnation! Oh my affectionate mother! Hast <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName> rewarded thee thus, for thy tender 
               solicitude for her was it for this, that thou saved me from the devouring flames of my native <placeName>St.
               Nicholas</placeName>! Was it for this, that thou didst exert all thy ingenuity, and saved me from the uplifted sword 
               of the enemy of <placeName>St. Domingo</placeName>!—Oh God! forgive this matricide! Forgive Theresa, who to save her 
               country, sacrificed a mother and a sister—Wretched <persName ref="#amanda">Amanda</persName>! and thrice wretched is thy sister, 
               who devoted thee to misery and death!</said>
            </p>
            <p>The body of escorts were now arrived at the <ecda:flora>Pimento</ecda:flora> grove—<persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName> 
               sprang from her carriage; hastened to the place where her mother and sister reposed at her departure. She cried in 
               the anguish of her soul, <said><rs type="person" ref="#paulina">My mother</rs>, my mother! where art thou!—come forth—let <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName> 
               embrace thee to her wretched bosom. Come <persName ref="#amanda">Amanda</persName>! dear <persName ref="#amanda">Amanda</persName>, come, and 
               save thy loving sister from black despair! Where, cruel enemy, where have he conducted them! If he have murdered my 
               dear mother and sister, let <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName>but embrace their clayey bodies, and while I bless the 
               enemies of the <name>Haytiens</name>!</said> But her grief was unheard by those, the loss of whom she bitterly 
               deplored; solemn silence occupied the grove, interrupted only by intervals with the moans and sobs of the men of arms, 
               who marked her anguish of soul, and were absorbed into pity. Whither now shall <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName> bend her 
               steps! No kind mother to guide her in life, or affectionate sister, to whom to impart the sorrow of her soul, or 
               participate with in innocent pleasure; friendless and disconsolate, she was now left exposed to many evils, and at
               a time too when the assiduous care of a mother was most essential in the preservation of her well being. 
               <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName> was on her way back to the camp of the kind <persName ref="#louverture_1743">Touissant L'Ourverture</persName> 
               to claim his fatherly protection, and seek a home in the bosom of those, to whom she had rendered herself dear by her 
               wisdom and virtue. The trampling of many <ecda:fauna ana="#military">horses</ecda:fauna> was heard rapidly approaching,
               and bending its way towards the same direction. It was a party of the <rs type="properAdjective">French</rs> troops, 
               and she was now to witness war in all its horors. The enemy of <rs type="properAdjective">Haytien</rs> freedom was now 
               near. The war trumpet now sounded the terrible blast from the engagement, and the <name>Revolutionists</name> like 
               <ecda:fauna>lions</ecda:fauna>, rushed on the the fight with a simultanous cry of <said>Freedom or Death!</said> The 
               <name>French</name>, great in number, fought in obedience to a cruel master. The <name>Haytiens</name> for liberty 
               and independence, and to obtain their rights of which they long have been unjustly deprived.
            </p>
            <p>The pass between the Mole and the village <placeName>St. Nicholas</placeName>, drank up the lives of hundreds in their 
               blood. The <name>French</name> retreated with precipitance, leaving their baggage with their gasping friends, on the 
               spot where victory perched on the standard of freedom: And now the conquerors had began to examine the property 
               deserted by the vanquished. A faint but mournful groan issued from a baggage cart forsaken by the enemy; directed by 
               the light of a flambeau, <persName ref="#inginac_0001">captain Inginac</persName> bent thither his nimble steps. Curiosity is lost in 
               surprise—joy succeeds sorrow—the lost ones are regained. It was <persName ref="#paulina">Madame Paulina</persName> and 
               <persName ref="#amanda">Amanda</persName>, the mother and sister of the unhappy <persName ref="#theresa">Theresa</persName>.
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
